<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="qualifiednames">
      <title>Qualified Names</title>
      <section xml:id="qual_owners">
        <title>Qualifiers and Owners</title>
        <para>
Virtuoso supports multiple namespaces for tables and procedures.  A table
or procedure is uniquely identified by a three part name consisting of
qualifier, owner and name separated by dots.
</para>
        <para>
Each connection has a current qualifier which is used as the default
qualifier for if a name does not specify a qualifier.  The owner can
be omitted from a name if the qualifier and name uniquely identify the
object, e.g.  DB..SYS_KEYS.
</para>
        <para>
Initially, all system objects have the qualifier DB and owner DBA.
</para>
        <para>
The default current qualifier of all connections is DB unless otherwise
specified using db.dba.user_set_qualifier.
</para>
        <para>
A user can be assigned a default qualifier set as current qualifier upon
login.  This is done with the stored procedure db.dba.user_set_qualifier.
</para>
        <screen>
user_set_qualifier  (in user varchar, in qualifier varchar)
</screen>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="defaultqualifiers">
        <title>Default Qualifiers</title>
        <para>
The default qualifier of the user is set to be the qualifier.  The names
are strings and thus case sensitive.
</para>
        <para>Example:</para>
        <programlisting>
db..user_set_qualifier ('U1', 'U1DATA');
</programlisting>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="userstmtid">
        <title>USE Statement, USE identifier</title>
        <para>
This sets the default qualifier for the connection in question.  The
identifier cannot be an expression. The identifier
is subject to whatever case conversions may be in effect.
</para>
        <tip>
          <title>See Also:</title>
          <para><link linkend="catidentifiers">CaseMode Configuration parameter</link>

  .</para>
        </tip>
        <para>
A quoted identifier will always pass in the
case it is entered. An unquoted identifier will be converted to upper
case if CaseMode so specifies.
</para>
      </section>
    </section>
