<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="virtuosospongerintro">
        <title>What Is The Sponger?</title>
        <para>The Virtuoso Sponger is the Linked Data middleware component of Virtuoso that generates
	Linked Data from a variety of data sources, supporting a wide variety of data representation
	and serialization formats. The sponger is transparently integrated into Virtuoso's SPARQL Query
	Processor where it delivers URI de-referencing within SPARQL query patterns, across disparate
	data spaces. It also delivers configurable smart HTTP caching services. Optionally, it can be
	used by the <link linkend="contentcrawlerrdf">Virtuoso Content Crawler</link>

   to periodically
	populate and replenish data within the native RDF Quad Store.
</para>
        <para>The sponger is a fully fledged HTTP proxy service that is also directly accessible via
	SOAP or REST interfaces.
</para>
        <para>As depicted below, OpenLink's broad portfolio of Linked-Data-aware products supports a number
	of routes for creating or consuming Linked Data. The Sponger provides a key platform for developers
	to generate quality data meshes from unstructured or semi-structured data sources.
</para>
        <figure xml:id="virtuosospongerdiagram" floatstyle="1">
          <title>OpenLink Linked Data generation options</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="Sponger_LinkedDataGenOptions_2014_v3.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>
Architecturally, the Sponger is comprised of a number of Cartridges two types of cartridges: Extractor
and Meta Cartridges. Extractor Cartridges focus on data extraction and transformation services while
the Meta Cartridges provide lookups and joins across other linked data spaces and Web 2.0 APIs. Both
cartridge types are themselves comprised of a data extractors and RDF Schema/Ontology Mapper
components.</para>
        <para>Cartridges are is highly customizable. Custom cartridges can be developed using any language
	supported by the Virtuoso Server Extensions API enabling structured linked data generation from
	resource types not available in the default Sponger Cartridge collection bundled -- as part of
	the Virtuoso <link xlink:href="http://s3.amazonaws.com/opldownload/uda/vad-packages/6.3/virtuoso/cartridges_dav.vad">Cartridges VAD package</link>

  .
</para>
        <figure xml:id="virtuosospongerdiagram_01" floatstyle="1">
          <title>Virtuoso metadata extraction &amp; RDF structured data generation</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="linked_data_gen_opts4.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="linked_data_gen_opts4.png"/>
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </section>
