<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="vspxappcode">
        <title>Application Code</title>
        <para>Most VSPX controls will support XML children specifying SQL code to
 run at various points of the page processing cycle.  The elements are:</para>
        <simplelist type="vert">
          <member>v:before-data-bind</member>
          <member>v:after-data-bind</member>
          <member>v:before-post</member>
          <member>v:before-render</member>
        </simplelist>
        <para>These elements will have a script tag as unique child, most often
 containing a CDATA section for escaping the SQL text.</para>
        <para>Additionally, most attributes of VSPX elements can have a SQL expression
 evaluated at initialization, pre data bind or after data bind time, as
 the case may be, depending on the attribute and its value.
 An attribute value beginning with <computeroutput>"--"</computeroutput>

 indicates evaluation on the initialization or the descending edge of the data
 bind pass.  An attribute value indicating <computeroutput>"--after"</computeroutput>

 specifies that the value is calculated on the returning edge of recursion of the data bind pass.</para>
        <para>Arbitrary HTML text may contain attributes with a data bound value.  The
 attributes should be in the XHTML namespace and have a text beginning with
 <computeroutput>"--"</computeroutput>

  .  The expression will be evaluated at
 render time, where the <emphasis>control</emphasis>

   variable refers to the
 enclosing VSPX template control, e.g. the page instance when at top level.</para>
        <section xml:id="vspxvspcompatinlinesql">
          <title>VSP Compatibility and In-Line SQL</title>
          <para>Arbitrary HTML text may contain &lt;?vsp ?&gt;, &lt;?V ?&gt; (equivalent of &lt;?= VSP notation) and
  &lt;?U ?&gt; (equivalent of &lt;?/ VSP notation) processing instructions.
  The code in question will be evaluated
  during the render pass, with control set to the closest enclosing VSPX
  control.
  Please note that the &lt;?= and &lt;?/ VSP shortcuts cannot be used inside VSPX pages as they are not valid processing-instructions.
  </para>
          <para>VSPX maintains backward compatibility with VSP through supporting the
  same processing instructions, but additionally requires the page source to be
  well formed XML.  VSP pages which are well formed in XML terms will run as
  such under with the VSPX extension, with the addition of the
  <computeroutput>v:page</computeroutput>

   top level element.</para>
          <para>The &lt;?vsp ?&gt; processing instruction expects a SQL statement.  The
  statement can be a compound statement ending in another &lt;?vsp ?&gt;
  processing instruction at the same nesting level under the same parent tag.
  The other pi's &lt;?V and &lt;?U  expect a SQL expression. </para>
          <note>
            <title>Note:</title>
            <para>&lt;?V ?&gt; is not permitted inside attributes without quotation,
    as this is not well formed XML.  When quoted, this notation in attributes
    has no special effect, hence the convention about the leading
    <computeroutput>"--"</computeroutput>

   and the <computeroutput>XHTML</computeroutput>

    namespace for HTML attributes with a computed value.</para>
          </note>
        </section>
      </section>
