<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="whatisvirtuoso">
      <title>What is Virtuoso?</title>
      <para>OpenLink Virtuoso is the first CROSS PLATFORM Universal Server to
		implement Web, File, and Database server functionality alongside Native XML
		Storage, and Universal Data Access Middleware, as a single server solution.
		It includes support for key Internet, Web, and Data Access standards such
		as: XML, XPATH, XSLT, SOAP, WSDL, UDDI, WebDAV, SMTP, SQL-92, ODBC, JDBC,
		and OLE-DB. Virtuoso currently supports the following Operating systems -
		Windows 95/98/NT/2000, Linux (Intel, Alpha, Mips, PPC), Solaris, AIX, HP-UX,
		Unixware, IRIX, Digital UNIX, DYNIX/PTX, FreeBSD, SCO, MacOS X.</para>
      <para>Virtuoso is a revolutionary, next generation, high-performance virtual database engine
    for the Distributed Computing Age. It is a core universal data access technology set to
    accelerate our advances into the emerging Information Age.</para>
      <para>Virtuoso provides transparent access to your existing data sources, which are typically
    databases from different database vendors.</para>
      <para>Through a single connection, Virtuoso will simultaneously connect your ODBC, JDBC,
    UDBC, OLE-DB client applications and services to data within Oracle, Microsoft SQL Server,
    DB/2, Informix, Progress, CA-Ingres and other ODBC compliant database engines. All your
    databases are treated as single logical unit.</para>
      <para>The diagram below depicts how applications that are built in conformance with industry
    standards (such as ODBC, JDBC, UDBC, and OLE-DB) only need to make a single connection via
    Virtuoso's Virtual Database Engine and end up with concurrent and real-time access to data
    within different database types.</para>
      <para>Further still, Virtuoso exposes all of its functionality to Web Services.
		This means that your existing infrastructure can be used support Web Services
		directly without any hint of replacement.
		</para>
    </section>
