<chapter id="EEIngres" >
  <title>OpenLink ODBC Driver for Ingres (Express Edition) </title>
  <sect1 id="eeingresmac">
    <title>OpenLink ODBC Driver for Ingres (Express Edition) for Mac OS X</title>
    <sect2 id="eeingresmacinstall">
      <title> Installation Guide</title>
      <para>The OpenLink ODBC Driver for
        Ingres (Express Edition) is distributed as a Disk image (DMG) file.
        Simply double click on the disk image 'mul6eing.dmg' to extract the
        installer mpkg file: </para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-00.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Double click on
        the mpkg file to run the installer and following the on screen
        instriuction as indicated below to complete the installation:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-01.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Installer Welcome Dialog for the OpenLink
        ODBC Driver
        for Ingres (Express Edition): </para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-02.gif"/></figure><para> Please review
        the readme file for installation requirements and known issues:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-03.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Please read the software license agreement before
        continuing your installation: </para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-04.gif"/></figure><para> Select
        destination volume for driver installation:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-05.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Choose to perform a custome or default
        installation of the driver:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-06.gif"/></figure>
      <para>If you chose the custom option select which of the
        components below are to be installed:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-07.gif"/></figure>
      <para>The Software must be installed as a user with
        Administrative privileges on the machine:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-08.gif"/></figure>
      <para>After the driver has been installed you will
        be prompted for a license file. If a license file already exists on
        the machine then select the 'use exisiting file' option. A trial
        (try) or full (buy) license can be obtain by selecting the 'try and
        buy' option which loads our online try and buy web page:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-09.gif"/></figure>
      <para>To obtain the trial license you must be a
        registered user on the OpenLink Web site and login with the
        username (e-mail address) and password for that user. Click on the
        'Shop' link to visit our online shop cart to purchases a full
        license if required:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-10.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Click on the 'download license' button to
        obtain the license file immediately and save to your desktop.
        Alternatively an auto e-mail will be sent to the registered users
        e-mail address with a link to their OpenLink Data Space (ODS) where
        all trial and full license files will be stored in the Briefcase
        for download at a later date.</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-11.gif"/></figure><para> Select
        the license file to be used for the installation:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-12.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Installation is complete:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-13.gif"/></figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="eeingresmacconf">
      <title>Configuration</title>
      <para>To configure an ODBC DSN, run the
        OpenLink iODBC Administrator located in the /Applications/iODBC folder:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-14.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Click on the add button to Choose the ODBC Driver the DSN
        should be created for:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-15.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Choose the OpenLink Ingres Driver (Express
        Edition) v6.0 from the list of available drivers:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-16.gif"/></figure>
      <para>In the Data Source tab, select a suitable DSN
        name and optional description for the Data Source to be
        created:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-17.gif"/></figure>
      <para>The Connection Tab requests the minimum
        paramters required to make a connection to the target
        database:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-18.gif"/></figure>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><emphasis>Hostname</emphasis> - the hostname of the server on which the Ingres
          Node is running</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>PortName</emphasis> - the Ingres instance Node name</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Database</emphasis> - the ase name of a valid database on the
          Node</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Username</emphasis> - the name of a valid Ingres user</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Advanced</emphasis> - additional optional configuration
          parameters:</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <table><title></title><tgroup><thead/><tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>RoleName</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Role used in DBMS.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>GroupName</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Group used in DBMS.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>DbmsUser</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>User ID for the DBMS session (-u flag).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>DbmsPassword</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>User's DBMS password.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ConnectionPool</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Use pooled connection: 'off' or 'on'.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>AutocommitMode</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Autocommit cursor handling: 'dbms', 'single',
                'multi'.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>SelectLoops</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Select loop processing: 'off' or 'on'.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>CursorMode</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Default cursor concurrency mode, which determines
                the concurrency of cursors that have no concurrency
                explicitly assigned. Available options are: 'dbms',
                'update', 'readonly'.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>VnodeUsage</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Allows the JDBC
                application to control the portions of the vnode
                information that are used to establish the connection to
                the remote DBMS server. Available options are: 'connect',
                'login'</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>CharEncode</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Specifies the Java character encoding used for
                conversions between Unicode and character data types.
                Generally, the character encoding is determined
                automatically by the driver from the DAS installation
                character set. This property allows an alternate
                character encoding to be specified (if desired) or a
                valid character encoding to be used when the driver is
                unable to map the server's character set.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>TimeZone</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Specifies the Ingres timezone associated with the
                client's location. Corresponds to the Ingres environment
                variable II_TIMEZONE_NAME and is assigned the same
                values. This property is not used directly by the driver
                but is sent to the DBMS and affects the processing of
                dates.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>DecimalChar</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Specifies the character to be used as the decimal
                point in numeric literals. Corresponds to the Ingres
                environment variable II_DECIMAL and is assigned the same
                values. This property is not used directly by the driver
                but is sent to the DBMS and affects the processing of
                query text.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>DateFormat</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Specifies the Ingres format for date literals.
                Corresponds to the Ingres environment variable
                II_DATE_FORMAT and is assigned the same values. This
                property is not used directly by the driver, but is sent
                to the DBMS and affects the processing of query
                text.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>MoneyFormat</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Specifies the Ingres format for money literals.
                Corresponds to the Ingres environment variable
                II_MONEY_FORMAT and is assigned the same values. This
                property is not used directly by the driver but is sent
                to the DBMS and affects the processing of query
                text.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>MoneyPrecision</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Specifies the precision of money data values.
                Corresponds to the Ingres environment variable
                II_MONEY_PREC and is assigned the same values. This
                property is not used directly by the driver but is sent
                to the DBMS and affects the processing of money
                values.</entry>
            </row>
      </tbody></tgroup></table><para>As indiacted above the paramters of
        the options and preferences tabs are not required for a basic
        connection:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-19.gif"/></figure>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><emphasis>Row Buffer Size</emphasis> - This attribute
          specifies the number of records to be transported over the
          network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1 to
          99.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Hide Login Dialog</emphasis> - Suppress the
          ODBC "Username" and "Password" login dialog box when
          interacting with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC compliant
          application.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Read Only connection</emphasis> - Specify
          whether the connection is to be read-only. Make sure the
          checkbox is unchecked to request a read/write
          connection.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Drop Catalog from Meta calls</emphasis> -
          Enable this option to have the catalog name not appear for
          tables, views and procedures when requesting database
          meta-data.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Drop Schema from Meta calls</emphasis> -
          Enable this option to have the schema-name not appear for
          tables, views and procedures when requesting database
          meta-data.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>SQLStatistics disabled</emphasis> - Check
          this box to have SQLStatistics() return an empty resultset. Use
          this if the underlying database does not support retrieving
          statistics about a table (e.g. what indexes there are on
          it).</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>No support of quoted identifier</emphasis> -
          If it is set, the call SQLGetInfo for
          'SQL_IDENTIFIER_QUOTE_CHAR' will return the space (" "). It can
          be used if DBMS doesn't support quoted SQL such as select *
          from "account"</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>No support of search string escape</emphasis>
          - If it is set, the call SQLGetInfo for
          'SQL_LIKE_ESCAPE_CLAUSE' will return the space character (" ").
          It can be used if DBMS doesn't support SQL escape
          patterns</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Patch of NULL size of SQL_CHAR</emphasis> -
          If set this option overrides the size of SQL_CHAR column type
          returned by the database with the value set in the text box (in
          bytes). With the default value of 0 the driver uses the size
          returned by the database.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>SQL_DBMS Name</emphasis> - Manually override
          the SQLGetInfo(SQL_DBMS_NAME) response returned by the driver.
          This is know to be required for products like Microsoft
          InfoPath for which the return the value should be "SQL
          Server".</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-20.gif"/></figure>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><emphasis>Initialization SQL</emphasis> - Lets you
          specify a file containing SQL statements that will be run
          against the database upon connection, automatically.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Cursor Sensitivity</emphasis> - Enables or
          disables the row version cache used with dynamic cursors. When
          dynamic cursor sensitivity is set high, the Cursor Library
          calculates checksums for each row in the current rowset and
          compares these with the checksums (if any) already stored in
          the row version cache for the same rows when fetched
          previously. If the checksums differ for a row, the row has been
          updated since it was last fetched and the row status flag is
          set to SQL_ROW_UPDATED. The row version cache is then updated
          with the latest checksums for the rowset. From the user's point
          of view, the only visible difference between the two
          sensitivity settings is that a row status flag can never be set
          to SQL_ROW_UPDATED when the cursor sensitivity is low. (The row
          status is instead displayed as SQL_ROW_SUCCESS.) In all other
          respects, performance aside, the two settings are the same -
          deleted rows don't appear in the rowset, updates to the row
          since the row was last fetched are reflected in the row data,
          and inserted rows appear in the rowset if their keys fall
          within the span of the rowset. If your application does not
          need to detect the row status SQL_ROW_UPDATED, you should leave
          the 'High Cursor Sensitivity' checkbox unchecked, as
          performance is improved. The calculation and comparison of
          checksums for each row fetched carries an overhead. If this
          option is enabled, the table oplrvc must have been created
          beforehand using the appropriate script for the target
          database.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>MaxRows Override</emphasis> - Allows you to
          define a limit on the maximum number of rows to returned from a
          query. The default value of 0 means no limit.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable AutoCommit</emphasis> - Change the
          default commit behaviour of the OpenLink Lite Driver. The
          default mode is AutoCommit mode (box unchecked).</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable Rowset Size Limit</emphasis> -
          Disable the limitation enforced by the cursor library. The
          limitation is enforced by default to prevent the Driver
          claiming all available memory in the event that a resultset is
          generated from an erroneous query is very large. The limit is
          normally never reached.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Defer fetching of long data</emphasis> -
          Defer fetching of LONG (BINARY, BLOB etc.) data unless
          explicitly requested in query. This provides significant
          performance increase when fields in query does not include LONG
          data fields.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Multiple Active Statements
            Emulation</emphasis> - Enables use of Multiple Active
          statements in an ODBC application even if the underlying
          database does not allow this, as it is emulated in the
          driver.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click on the 'Test Data Source' button to make a
        connection to the database to verify connectivity:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-21.gif"/></figure>
      <para>Enter a vaild username and pasword for the
        database:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-22.gif"/></figure>
      <para>A successful connection to the database has
        been made:</para>
      <figure><graphic fileref="ee-ing-23.gif"/></figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="eeingreswin">
    <title>OpenLink ODBC Driver for Ingres (Express Edition) for
      Windows</title>
    <sect2 id="eeingreswininst"> <title>Installation</title>
      <para>The OpenLink ODBCDriver for Ingres (Express Edition) is distributed as a Windows MSI installer. Simply double click on the installer 'ntl6eing.msi' to commence the installation: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst01.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Installer Welcome Dialog for the OpenLink ODBCDriver for Ingres (Express Edition): </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst02.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Please read the software license agreement and accept before continuing your installation: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst03.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Before installation you will be prompted for a license file. If a license file already exists on the machine, then select the 'use exisiting file' option. A trial (try) or full (buy) license can be obtained by selecting the 'try and buy' option, which loads OpenLink's online try and buy web page: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst04.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>To obtain the trial license, you must be a registered user on the OpenLinkWeb site and login with your username (e-mail address) and password. Click on the 'Shop' link to visit OpenLink's online shop cart to purchase a full license, if required: </para>
      <para>Click on the 'download license' button to immediately obtain the license file and save it to your desktop. Alternatively, an auto-generated e-mail will be sent to your registered e-mail address. This email will contain a link to your OpenLinkData Space ( ODS). The OpenLInkData Space ( ODS) contains copies of all trial and full license files in a Briefcase for download at a later date. </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst05.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Select the license file to be used for the installation: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst06.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Choose to perform a custom, typical or complete installation of the driver: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst07.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Select the features to be installed: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst08.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Click the install button to begin the installation of components: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst09.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Installation in progress: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst10.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>The Software installation is complete and ready for use: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWininginst11.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="eeingreswinconf"> <title>Configuration</title>
      <para>To configure an ODBCDSN, run the ODBCAdministrator located in the Administrative Tools section of the Control Panel: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf01.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Click on the Drivers tab to confirm the OpenLinkIngres ODBCDriver [Express Edition][6.0] has been successfully installed: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf02.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>From either the User or System DSN tabs, click on the Add button and select the OpenLinkIngres ODBCDriver [Express Edition][6.0] from the list : </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf03.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>In the Data Source tab, select a suitable DSN name and optional description for the Data Source to be created: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf04.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>The Connection tab requests the minimum parameters required to make a connection to the target database: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf05.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Host</emphasis>: This is the fully qualified
          hostname or IP address of the machine hosting the DBMS you
          wish to access, e.g., dbms-server.example.com, or
          192.168.155.123. Any hostname which will be resolved by your
          local DNS
          is acceptable.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>PortName</emphasis>: This is the port on which
          Ingres is listening</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Database</emphasis>: This is the name of the Ingres
          database to which you want to connect</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Login ID</emphasis>: This is a valid user name for
          the Ingres database</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Password</emphasis>: This is a valid password for
          the Ingres database</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click next to verify that all settings are correct or uncheck the check box to delay testing to a later stage. </para>
      <para>The advanced button displays additional, optional parameters that can be configured: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf06.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <table>
        <title/>
        <tgroup>
          <thead/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>RoleName</entry>
              <entry>Role used in DBMS.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>GroupName</entry>
              <entry>Group used in DBMS.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>DbmsUser</entry>
              <entry>User ID for the DBMS session (-u
                flag).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                DbmsPassword</entry>
              <entry>User's DBMS password.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                ConnectionPool</entry>
              <entry>Use pool connectino: 'off' or
                'on.'</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                AutocommitMode</entry>
              <entry>Autocommit cursor handling: 'dbms',
                'single', 'multi. (default - 'dbms')</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                SelectLoops</entry>
              <entry>Select loop processing: 'off' or
                'on.' (default - 'off')</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CursorMode</entry>
              <entry>Default cursor concurrency mode,
                which determines the concurrency of cursors that have no
                concurrency explicitly assigned. Available options are:
                'dbms', 'update', 'readonly.' (default - 'dbms')</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>VnodeUsage</entry>
              <entry>Allows the JDBC
                application to control the portions of the vnode
                information that are used to establish the connection to
                the remote DBMS server. Available options are
                'connect','login' (default - 'connect').</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>CharEncode</entry>
              <entry>Specifies the character encoding for
                the conversions between Unicode and character data types.
                Generally, the character encoding is determined
                automatically by the driver from the DAS installation
                character set. This property allows an alternate character
                encoding to be specified (if desired) or a valid character
                encoding to be used when the driver is unable to map the
                server's character set.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>TimeZone</entry>
              <entry>Specifies the Ingres timezone
                associated with the client's location. Corresponds to the
                Ingres environment variable II_TIMEZONE_NAME and is
                assigned the same values. This property is not used
                directly by the driver but is sent to the DBMS and affects
                the processing of dates.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                DecimalChar</entry>
              <entry>Specifies the character to be used as
                the decimal point in numeric literals. Corresponds to the
                Ingres environment variable II_DECIMAL and is assigned the
                same values. This property is not used directly by the
                driver but is sent to the DBMS and affects the processing
                of query text.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>DateFormat</entry>
              <entry>Specifies the Ingres format for date
                literals. Corresponds to the Ingres environment variable
                II_DATE_DECIMAL and is assigned the same values. This
                property is not used directly by the driver but is sent to
                the DBMS and affects the processing of query text.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                MoneyFormat</entry>
              <entry>Specifies the Ingres format for money
                literals. Corresponds to the Ingres environment variable
                II_MONEY_FORMAT and is assigned the same values. This
                property is not used directly by the driver but is sent to
                the DBMS and affects the processing of query text..</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                MoneyPrecision</entry>
              <entry>Specifies the precision of money data
                values. Corresponds to the Ingres environment variable
                II_MONEY_PREC and is assigned the same values. This
                property is not used directly by the driver but is sent to
                the DBMS and affects the processing of money values.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>As indicated above, the parameters on the options and preferences tabs are not required for a basic connection. </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf17.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Drop Catalog name from DatabaseMetaData
            calls</emphasis> - Enable this option to have the catalog name
          not appear for tables, views, and procedures when requesting
          database meta-data.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Drop Schema name from DatabaseMetaData
            calls</emphasis> - Enable this option to have the schema-name
          not appear for tables, views, and procedures when requesting
          database meta-data.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Return an empty ResultSet for
            SQLStatistics</emphasis> - Check this box to have
          SQLStatistics() return an empty resultset. Use this if the
          underlying database does not support retrieving statistics
          about a table, e.g., what indexes there are on it.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable support of quoted identifier</emphasis> -
          If it is set, the call SQLGetInfo for
          'SQL_IDENTIFIER_QUOTE_CHAR' will return the space (" "). It
          can be used if the DBMS does not support quoted SQL, e.g., select
          * from "account."</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable support of search pattern escape</emphasis>
          - If it is set, the call SQLGetInfo for
          'SQL_LIKE_ESCAPE_CLAUSE' will return the space (" "). It can
          be used if the DBMS does not support SQL escape
          patterns.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Patch of NULL size of SQL_CHAR</emphasis> - If set,
          this option overrides the size of SQL_CHAR column type
          returned by the database with the value set in the text box
          (in bytes). With the default value of 0, the driver uses the
          size returned by the database.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf08.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable Interactive Login</emphasis> - Suppress the
          ODBC
          "Username" and "Password" login dialog box when interacting
          with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC compliant
          application.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Row Buffer Size</emphasis> - This attribute
          specifies the number of records to be transported over the
          network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1 to
          99.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Max rows override</emphasis> - Allows you to define
          a limit on the maximum number of rows to be returned from a
          query. The default value of 0 means no limit.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Initial SQL</emphasis> - Lets you specify a file
          containing SQL statements that will be automatically run
          against the database upon connection.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Dynamic Cursor Sensitivity</emphasis> - Enables or
          disables the row version cache used with dynamic cursors.
          When dynamic cursor sensitivity is set high, the Cursor
          Library calculates checksums for each row in the current
          rowset and compares these with the checksums (if any) already
          stored in the row version cache for the same rows when
          fetched previously. If the checksums differ for a row, the
          row has been updated since it was last fetched, and the row
          status flag is set to SQL_ROW_UPDATED. The row version cache
          is then updated with the latest checksums for the rowset.
          From the user's point of view, the only visible difference
          between the two sensitivity settings is that a row status
          flag can never be set to SQL_ROW_UPDATED, when the cursor
          sensitivity is low. (The row status is instead displayed as
          SQL_ROW_SUCCESS.) In all other respects, performance aside,
          the two settings are the same - deleted rows do not appear in
          the rowset, updates to the row since the row was last fetched
          are reflected in the row data, and inserted rows appear in
          the rowset if their keys fall within the span of the rowset.
          If your application does not need to detect the row status
          SQL_ROW_UPDATED, you should leave the 'High Cursor
          Sensitivity' checkbox unchecked, as performance is improved.
          The calculation and comparison of checksums for each row
          fetched carries an overhead. If this option is enabled, the
          table oplrvc must have been created beforehand using the
          appropriate OpenLink script for the target database.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Enable logging to the log file:</emphasis> -
          Specifies the full path to a text file. If the associated
          checkbox is checked, and a file is passed, the driver will
          log auto-generate a clientside ODBC trace.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf09.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable AutoCommit</emphasis> -
          Change the default commit behaviour of the OpenLink
          Driver. The default mode is AutoCommit (box
          unchecked).</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable Rowset Size Limit</emphasis> - Disable the
          limitation enforced by the cursor library. The limitation is
          enforced by default to prevent the Driver claiming all
          available memory in the event that a resultset generated from
          an erroneous query is very large. The limit is normally never
          reached.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Multiple Active Statements Emulation</emphasis> -
          Enables use of Multiple Active statements in an ODBC application
          even if the underlying database does not allow this, as it is
          emulated in the driver.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>SQL_DBMS Name</emphasis> - Manually override the
          SQLGetInfo(SQL_DBMS_NAME)
          response returned by the driver. This is required for
          products like Microsoft InfoPath for which
          the return value must be "SQL Server".</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click on the <emphasis>Test Data Source</emphasis>button to verify that a successful connection can be made to the database. </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWiningconf10.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
