<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!--
  $Id: clientcompinstall.xml,v 1.10.4.8 2005/06/15 16:35:46 cvs Exp $
  (C)Copyright 1996-2018 OpenLink Software
-->
<chapter id="clientcompinstall" >
  <title>OpenLink ODBC Driver (Multi-Tier Edition) Client Component</title>
  <abstract>
    <para>
This chapter describes the ODBC client component of OpenLink Universal Data Access (UDA).</para>
    <para>ODBC stands for Open Database Connectivity, a data-access API implementation
from Microsoft that conforms to the X/Open SQL CLI specification. ODBC links ODBC compliant
applications to ODBC Drivers via the ODBC Driver Manager.</para>
    <para>ODBC Driver Managers exist on other platforms such as Mac, Unix and Linux.
These platforms usually make use of the &quot;iODBC Driver Manager&quot;.
Additional information regarding iODBC can be obtained from:
<ulink url="http://www.iodbc.org/">www.iodbc.org</ulink>.</para>
  </abstract>
  <chapterinfo>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>ODBC</keyword>
      <keyword>ODBC Driver</keyword>
      <keyword>ODBC Drivers</keyword>
      <keyword>Generic Client</keyword>
      <keyword>Client</keyword>
      <keyword>Install</keyword>
      <keyword>Installation Guide</keyword>
      <keyword>Unix</keyword>
      <keyword>Mac</keyword>
      <keyword>OS X</keyword>
      <keyword>Windows</keyword>
      <keyword>Lite</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>
<!-- ======================================== -->
  <sect1 id="clientcompw32">
    <sect1info>
      <keywordset>
        <keyword>Windows Client</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </sect1info>
    <title>Generic Client for Windows</title>
    <anchor id="clientcompinstallclientcompw32cci" /><!-- For Menu.Ini -->
    <sect2 id="cci">
      <title>Installation (32-bit)</title>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>After downloading the OpenLink Data Access Driver Suite client
components from our Website, Unzip the contents of the ZIP format archive
into a temporary installation directory on your client machine.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the setup.exe installer program from the temporary
installation directory and then follow the on screen prompts.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>After installation you will be able to safely remove the files
in the temporary directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
&mt64bitinstsect;
    <sect2 id="dsnconfigw">
      <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
      <para>Once you have completed the installation process, proceed to create a
new ODBC Data Source Name (DSN) using the ODBC Driver Manager.</para>
      <para>The ODBC Driver Manager is in the Windows Control panel. Windows 2000 and
Windows XP have it within Administrative tools. The figure below depicts
ODBC v3.5 Driver Manager displaying a list of installed ODBC Drivers.</para>
      <figure id="odbccl2" float="1">
        <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
        <graphic fileref="odbccl2.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="Confudsn">
      <title>ODBC System &amp; User Data Sources</title>
      <para>ODBC Driver Manager can create User, System, and File DSNs.
Here are the steps for creating a User or System DSN:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Decide whether the DSN should be a USER DSN so that it is
available for all users, or a USER DSN is required for access by the current
user only.</para>
          <para>In the ODBC Driver Manager pick the SYSTEM or USER tab.
In this example the SYSTEM tab is chosen, and the current System DSNs are shown:</para>
          <figure id="odbccl3" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="odbccl3.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Pick the ODBC Driver to be used to create your ODBC DSN, in the
case of the OpenLink Universal Data Access Driver Suite 5.0, this would be the Driver
identified below as "OpenLink Generic ODBC Driver".</para>
          <figure id="odbccl4" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="odbccl4.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The ODBC Driver manager now launches the selected driver
code so that the DSN may be configured. In this example it will present the
OpenLink ODBC Data Source Configuration dialog (depicted below).</para>
          <figure id="dsn05" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="dsn05.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
          <para>Configure the fields of the ODBC "System" or "User" DSN
Configuration dialog in the manner explained below:</para>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Name</title>
            <para>(Datasource) The name of the ODBC DSN, this is how you will
interact with the OpenLink ODBC Driver from within ODBC compliant applications
once your ODBC DSN has been created.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Description</title>
            <para>Additional information that further describes the ODBC DSN that
you are creating.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Server</title>
            <para>Selected Zero Configuration service name or
<computeroutput>&lt;hostname or IP address&gt;:&lt;port&gt;</computeroutput>
of running Broker.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <para>The easiest way to complete this field is to select a machine
from the drop-down list-box. This list of servers is automatically generated
by the Zero Configuration service, so you only need to chose which machine
you wish to reach.</para>
          <para>Alternatively, enter the hostname or IP address that identifies a Server
Machine running OpenLink Server Components, that speak the OpenLink Data Access
Protocol. Follow this with a colon and the TCP/IP Port number of the Broker
to contact. This corresponds to the Listen parameter on the target Broker.</para>
          <para>This example shall now assume the selection of a server from a picklist.</para>
          <figure id="odbccl5" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="odbccl5.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Now select the database and configuration details:</para>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Domain</title>
            <para>This is how you pick the Database Engine Type that your ODBC DSN
is to be associated with e.g. Informix 7, Oracle 7, Progress 7 etc.</para>
            <para>The default offered from the Zero Configuration is typically accepted.
An alternative compatable Domain may be chosen for a specific customisation.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Database</title>
            <para>This is how an actual database
name within the Provider Type Domain is identified, for instance "stores7"
indicates an "Informix 7" database called "stores7".  This option corresponds to
the Database parameter in the preference files.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Connection Options</title>
            <para>This is where you place any database specific database connection
options. This field in a majority of cases should be left blank by
default.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Connect now..</title>
            <para>When this tick box is checked, a test connection
is made to verify the Data Source connection.</para>
            <para>If there is no check then the Login ID and Password fields are
ignored, and no test is performed.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Login ID</title>
            <para>The default database UserID to use when logging on to a remote
database engine (identified by the Domain above).</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Password</title>
            <para>The Password for the login of the above UserID.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <figure id="dsn06" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="dsn06.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When a test connection fails, the error message
is now displayed:</para>
          <figure id="dsn07" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="dsn07.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Now define additonal connection parameters:</para>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Read-only connection</title>
            <para>Specify whether the connection is to be "Read-only".
Make sure the checkbox is unchecked to request a "Read/Write" connection.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Defer fetching of long data</title>
            <para>Check this box to defer the fetching of long data.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Disable interactive login</title>
            <para>Suppress the ODBC "Username" and "Password" login
dialog box when interacting with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC compliant
application.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Row Buffer Size</title>
            <para>This attribute specifies the number of records to be
transported over the network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1
to 99.</para>
          </formalpara>
          <figure id="dsn08" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="dsn08.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The list of parameters for the DSN are now shown.
The Test Data Source button will trigger a test of the DSN using the
existing login parameters.</para>
          <figure id="dsn08b" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="dsn08b.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If a test is requested, the results are shown:</para>
          <figure id="dsn08c" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="dsn08c.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
          <para>Press the Finish button to save the DSN.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>This completes the DSN configuration.
It will be listed in the ODBC Driver Manager.</para>
          <figure id="dsn09" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="dsn09.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <sect3 id="manualdsn">
        <title>Manual Selection of Server</title>
        <para>The previous example used a server that was picked from the
list constructed by the zero configuration. The server you wish to
use might not be in this list if it is not a local machine that
can be discovered. In this case it is necessary to complete the
server field manually with the host name or IP number, and the
port number.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Complete the fields for Data Source Name and Description as
before. In the server field, enter the TCPIP address and port of the server
machine.</para>
            <figure id="dsn10" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
              <graphic fileref="dsn10.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The connection parameter page will load without any
fields completed.</para>
            <figure id="dsn11" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
              <graphic fileref="dsn11.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
            <para>Complete the fields for database connection.</para>
            <figure id="dsn12" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
              <graphic fileref="dsn12.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Complete the fields for additional connection parameters.</para>
            <figure id="dsn13" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
              <graphic fileref="dsn13.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>This completes the DSN configuration.
It will be listed in the ODBC Driver Manager.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="Creatfdsn">
      <title>Creating a File Data Source</title>
      <para>This format of ODBC DSN enables the creation of centralized ODBC DSNs on
a designated NT or Windows 95 Server machine, thereby reducing the
administrative overhead of ODBC DSN configuration for every single machine
within your infrastructure.</para>
      <para>The steps for creating an ODBC File DSN are as follows:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Select the File DSN Tab from the ODBC Driver Manger.
Press the Add button.</para>
          <figure id="filedsn01" float="1">
            <title>File Data Sources</title>
            <graphic fileref="filedsn01.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Pick the ODBC Driver to be used to create your ODBC DSN, in the
case of the OpenLink Universal Data Access Driver Suite 5.0, this would be the Driver
identified below as "OpenLink Generic ODBC Driver".</para>
          <figure id="odbccl4" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="odbccl4.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter a name that describes your File DSN (e.g. "Sales by Region"
as depicted below) for future use when interacting with it from ODBC compliant
application and environments. At present to get full compatability within the
Admin Assistant, you must end your dsn name with the extension ".dsn".
So for this example the DSN name would be "Sales by Region.dsn".</para>
          <figure id="odbccl6" float="1">
            <title>File Data Sources</title>
            <graphic fileref="odbccl6.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Verify the displayed paramters are correct, and confirm
by hitting Finish button.</para>
          <figure id="odbccl7" float="1">
            <title>File Data Sources</title>
            <graphic fileref="odbccl7.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter a Description and define the location of the
server either by selection, or enter it manually.</para>
          <para>Note the name is not defined here as the filename defines
the DSN.</para>
          <figure id="odbccl8" float="1">
            <title>File Data Sources</title>
            <graphic fileref="odbccl8.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Complete the fields of the ODBC File DSN.
Enter Domain, Database, Server. See above for details of each.</para>
          <para>The File DSN must be verified immediately, so the
Login ID and password are required. The Next button will be
disabled until login details are provided.</para>
          <figure id="odbccl9" float="1">
            <title>File Data Sources</title>
            <graphic fileref="odbccl9.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Complete the fields for additional connection parameters.</para>
          <figure id="dsn13" float="1">
            <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
            <graphic fileref="dsn13.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>This concludes the File DSN generation.
The DSN will appear in the list under the File DSN Tab of
the ODBC Driver Manger.</para>
          <figure id="filedsn04" float="1">
            <title>File Data Sources</title>
            <graphic fileref="filedsn04.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="Advanced_Settings">
      <title>Advanced Settings</title>
      <para>The settings in this section have default values which are recommended
in most situations.</para>
      <para>If you run a complex query through the database it may take a long time
before any data is actually returned. In this situation you may need to
increase the ReceiveTimeout value, described below, only to cater for it. 2
Minutes (default) is usually more than adequate.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>32bit Client Advanced Settings.</title>
        <para>Client global configuration information is contained in the sub section
OPENLINK.INI of the registry. Windows 32bit platforms use the registry to store
all configuration information. To edit or view to registry, run the
regedit program. To view the OpenLink settings expand the following
section:</para>
        <screen>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SOFTWARE\ODBC\OPENLINK.INI</screen>
        <para>Important values that you may need to change are listed in the table
below. The default values are recommended in most cases:</para>
        <table>
          <tgroup>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Sub Section</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Key</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Description</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Communications</para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>BrokerTimeout</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The amount of time the client will wait for a connection to an agent.
The default value is 30. Value is measured in seconds.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>ReceiveTimeout</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The amount of time the client will wait for a query to return with
data. The default value is 120. Value is measured in seconds.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>ShowErrors</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>With this set to yes any OpenLink messages will be displayed in
a dialog box. If this is set to no, OpenLink messages will not be
displayed.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>ServerTypes</para>
                </entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>&lt;Name&gt;=</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Each key name in this section represents a different provider
type. To add a provider type simply add a new line using the same syntax as
the default types.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </formalpara>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
<!-- ======================================== -->
  <sect1 id="macinstall">
    <sect1info>
      <keywordset>
        <keyword>Mac Client</keyword>
        <keyword>Mac Classic</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </sect1info>
    <title>Generic Client For Macintosh OS 8.6+</title>
    <para>There are several ODBC Driver Managers distributed for the Classic
Macintosh OS. OpenLink Software distributes iODBC, an
Open Source, Cross-Platform, LGPL and BSDI licensed, ODBC 3.5-compliant Driver
Manager maintained by OpenLink. Additional information regarding iODBC can be
obtained from <ulink url="http://www.iodbc.org/">http://www.iodbc.org</ulink>.</para>
    <para>The iODBC Driver Manager requires Mac OS 9 or later; the OpenLink Generic
Client Driver for ODBC may be used on System 7 through Mac OS 9, with any
ODBC 2.x- or 3.x-compliant Driver Manager.</para>
    <para>The OpenLink ODBC Client Components for Macintosh Classic comprise the
following:</para>
    <table>
      <tgroup>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Component</entry>
            <entry>Purpose</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>iODBC Driver Manager</entry>
            <entry>A shared library that links ODBC compliant applications to ODBC
  Drivers</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Generic ODBC Driver</entry>
            <entry>A shared library that provides database connectivity and data access
  services to ODBC compliant applications</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Sample ODBC Applications</entry>
            <entry>Simple programs that can be used to verify your ODBC installation
  and working environment</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <sect2 id="maccci">
      <title>Installation</title>
      <para>After downloading the OpenLink Data Access Driver Suite client components
from our Website, uncompress the contents of the Stuffit format archive into a
temporary location on your client machine. The Desktop is often best.</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass01jpg" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass01.jpg" format="jpg"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>Double click the 'OpenLink MacOS ODBC Client 5.0' icon to launch the
installer. Click OK at the splash screen.</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass02gif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass02.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>Check the contents of the 'Read Me'. Then click Continue.</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass03gif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass03.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>Read and Agree to the Software License.</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass04gif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass04.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>There are two types of installation. The Easy Install option is best
for most users, and will install the iODBC Driver Manager, if no
other Driver Manager is present.</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass05gif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass05.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>If you need to replace an older Driver Manager (Merant, Visigenic,
Intersolv), select the Custom Install, and check off all appropriate
components. The iODBC Driver Manager will only run on PowerPC machines, under
Mac OS 9 or later.  If you're installing on an older Mac, running Mac OS 8.1 or
earlier, you can use Custom Install to get the 68K components you'll need.</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass06gif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass06.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>Press the Install button to start the installation.
You will be prompted to select a location for Sample Applications and
other files.</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass07gif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass07.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>You Macintosh will need to be restarted after installation has completed.
You will be given the opportunity to save any open documents. </para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass08gif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass08.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>Installation will proceed.</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass09gif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass09.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>After installation you
may safely delete the files in the temporary location ('OpenLink MacOS ODBC
Client 4.1', 'OplMacClient-4.1.sit', mmoczzzz.hqx).</para>
      <figure id="MacOSClass10jpg" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacOSClass10.jpg" format="jpg"></graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="macdsn">
      <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
      <para>Once you have completed the installation process, proceed to create a
new ODBC DSN using the OpenLink ODBC Administrator (formerly ODBC Setup PPC)
control panel.</para>
      <para>The OpenLink ODBC Administrator for Mac Classic currently supports the creation
of User and File DSNs.</para>
      <para>If in Multiple Users mode, a User DSN is only available to the user who creates the
data source.  Its parameters are stored in that user's settings file:
<computeroutput>Preferences/ODBC Preferences PPC</computeroutput>. </para>
      <para>If in Single User mode, a User DSN is only available to the whole system so that
any user, including the system itself, will be able to use that data source.
Its parameters are stored in the System settings file:
<computeroutput>System Folder/Preferences/ODBC Preferences PPC</computeroutput>. </para>
      <para>A File DSN is a special 'mobile' data source that stores the data source
information associated with the Driver in a file, which may then be copied and
shared among different users and ODBC application host machines. </para>
      <para>File DSNs are usually created when the same DSN needs to be used by many
different users, from many different workstations.  File DSNs may be passed
from Macintosh to Macintosh, or User to User in Multiple Users mode, and will
be usable by anyone with the same ODBC Drivers installed.  By default, File
DSNs are found in: <computeroutput>System Folder/Preferences/ODBC
File Data Sources.</computeroutput>
      </para>
      <para>Most often, a User DSN will be appropriate for use on a Macintosh running
the Classic Mac OS.</para>
      <sect3 id="configusermacdsn">
        <title>User Data Source Names</title>
        <para>To create a new User DSN, open the ODBC Setup PPC control panel. Hit
the Add button.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass11gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass11.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Pick the ODBC Driver to be used to create your ODBC DSN, in the case
of the OpenLink Universal Data Access Driver Suite 5.0, this would be the
Driver identified below as "OpenLink Generic ODBC PPC".</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass12gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass12.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Once you have selected
the "OpenLink Generic 32 Bit Driver v5.0", you will be presented with the
OpenLink ODBC Data Source Configuration dialog (depicted below).</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass13gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass13.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>The Datasource settings are only important to your Client
machine; the OpenLink Server, Database, and Optional Server settings should
be provided by your Database Administrator, or whoever is handling the Server-side
components of the OpenLink Universal Data Access Suite.</para>
        <note>
          <title>Note:</title>
          <para>The connections will not succeed until Server-side components
are installed and properly configured.</para>
        </note>
        <para>Explanations of each field follows:</para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Datasource Name</title>
          <para>The name of the ODBC DSN. This is how you will interact with the
OpenLink ODBC Driver from within ODBC compliant applications once your ODBC
DSN has been created.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Comment</title>
          <para>Additional information that further describes the ODBC DSN that
you are creating. This is generally visible whenever a list of DSNs is
generated.  This option corresponds to the Description parameter in the
preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Domain</title>
          <para>This is how you pick the Database Engine Type (also called a DBMS, or
DataBase Management System) that your ODBC DSN is to be associated with, e.g.
Informix 7, Oracle 9, Progress 8.3B, etc.  This option corresponds to the ServerType
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Protocol</title>
          <para>Select the network transport protocol used to connect your ODBC DSN
with a remote database engine. This will be TCP/IP in most installations.
This option corresponds to the Protocol parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Hostname</title>
          <para>Enter the hostname or IP address that identifies a Server Machine
running OpenLink Server Components, that speak the OpenLink Data Access
Protocol.  This option corresponds to the Host parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Port</title>
          <para>Enter the TCP port number of the Broker to contact. This corresponds
to the Listen parameter on the target Broker.  This option corresponds to the
Port parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Database Name</title>
          <para>This is how an actual database
name within the Provider Type Domain is identified, for instance "stores7"
indicates an "Informix 7" database called "stores7".  This option corresponds to
the Database parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Username</title>
          <para>The default database UserID to be used when logging on to a remote
database engine (identified by the Provider Type above).
Generally left blank on shared machines.  This option corresponds to the User
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Server Name</title>
          <para>This is where you place any database specific database connection
options. This field in a majority of cases should be left blank by default.
Your Database Administrator (DBA) should give you any special
settings.  This option corresponds to the Options parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Read-only connection</title>
          <para>Forces the connection is to be "Read-only". Make sure the checkbox
is unchecked to request a "Read/Write" connection.  This option corresponds to
the ReadOnly parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>No Login Dialog Box</title>
          <para>Suppress the ODBC "Username" and "Password" login dialog box when
interacting with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC compliant application.
This should be unchecked if the database requires this
information.  This option corresponds to the NoLoginBox parameter in the
preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Defer fetching of long data</title>
          <para>Check this box to defer the fetching of long data. See the Release
Notes section for more details.  This option corresponds to the DeferLongFetch
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Row Buffer Size</title>
          <para>This attribute specifies the number of records to be transported over
the network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1 to 999.
Smaller values are generally appropriate when each row contains large
records; larger values are generally appropriate for smaller record sizes.
Adjusting this value up and down can improve or degrade performance
substantially, both for your own connection and for other users of the same
Database, so check with your DBA before changing it from the default (30).
This option corresponds to the FetchBufferSize parameter in the preference
files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>Click OK, and you'll see your new DSN in the list.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass14gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass14.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Now, to verify that your settings are correct and all is functional,
select the new DSN, and click Test. You'll be presented with the
following dialog.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass15gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass15.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Input the correct password for the username shown.
You can connect as another user, if you wish, by simply typing a
different username in the field. To verify that your settings have all
"stuck", you can click the Database tab:</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass16gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass16.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>The "About" tab shows
you basic information about the Driver on which the DSN is
based.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass17gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass17.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>When you click OK, your Mac will think for a moment, while it makes
a connection to the remote Data Source. If all is well, you will be
presented with this Success message:</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass18gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass18.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="configfilemacdsn">
        <title>Configuring File Data Sources</title>
        <para>To create a new File DSN, open the ODBC Setup PPC control panel.
Click on the File DSN tab, and follow the steps below:</para>
        <para>Click the Add button.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass19gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass19.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Pick the ODBC Driver to be used to create your ODBC DSN.
As with the User DSN, this would be the Driver identified below as
"OpenLink Generic ODBC PPC". Input a name for the File DSN, and any
description. Click "Finish" or "OK".</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass20gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass20.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>File DSNs are configured through the login screens, as if you were
connecting through a User DSN. Starting with the Identity
tab, input the appropriate Username and Password. (The Password will not be
saved in the DSN, as this would present a significant security risk.)</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass21gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass21.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>The OpenLink Server, Database, and Optional Server settings seen in
the User DSN configuration screen are combined into the Database tab.
Again, these should be provided by your Database Administrator, or
whoever is handling the Server-side components of the OpenLink Universal Data
Access Suite.</para>
        <note>
          <title>Note:</title>
          <para>The connections will not succeed until Server-side components
are installed and properly configured.</para>
        </note>
        <figure id="MacOSClass16gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass16.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Explanations of each field in the Database tab follows:</para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Domain</title>
          <para>This is how you pick the Database Engine Type (also called a DBMS, or
DataBase Management System) that your ODBC DSN is to be associated with,
e.g. Informix 7, Oracle 9, Progress 8.3B, etc.  This option corresponds to the ServerType
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Name</title>
          <para>This is how an actual database name within the Provider Type Domain is
identified, for instance "stores7" indicates an "Informix 7" database called
"stores7".  This option corresponds to the Database
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Server</title>
          <para>This is where you place any database specific database connection
options. This field in a majority of cases should be left blank by default.
Your Database Administrator (DBA) should give you any special settings.
This option corresponds to the Options
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Hostname</title>
          <para>Enter the hostname or IP address that identifies a Server Machine
running OpenLink Server Components, that speak the OpenLink Data Access
Protocol.  This option corresponds to the Host
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Protocol</title>
          <para>Select the network transport protocol used to connect your ODBC DSN
with a remote database engine. This will be TCP/IP in most installations.
This option corresponds to the Protocol
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Port</title>
          <para>Enter the TCP port number of the Broker to contact. This corresponds
to the Listen parameter on the target Broker.
This option corresponds to the Port
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Defer fetching of long data</title>
          <para>Check this box to defer the fetching of long data. See the Release
Notes section for more details.  This option corresponds to the DeferLongFetch
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Read-only connection</title>
          <para>Forces the connection is to be "Read-only". Make sure the checkbox
is unchecked to request a "Read/Write" connection.
This option corresponds to the ReadOnly
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Row Buffer Size</title>
          <para>This attribute specifies the number of records to be transported over
the network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1 to 999. Smaller
values are generally appropriate when each row contains large records; larger
values are generally appropriate for smaller record sizes. Adjusting this
value up and down can improve or degrade performance substantially, both
for your own connection and for other users of the same Database, so check
with your DBA before changing it from the default (30).
This option corresponds to the FetchBufferSize
parameter in the preference files.</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>The About tab, here, refers to the Driver you've selected for this
DSN.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass17gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass17.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Click OK when all settings are correct, and you will see the
new DSN available in the File DSN list. Sharing this DSN with
other users and machines may be accomplished by going to the 'ODBC File Data
Sources' folder, found in the 'Preferences' folder, within your System
Folder.  Other Macintosh Classic OpenLink clients may use the file by placing it in
the same location on their machine.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass22gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass22.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="tracemacdsn">
      <title>Tracing Data Sources</title>
      <para>From the Tracing Tab of the iODBC Data Source Administrator,
the level of Tracing can be configured.</para>
      <figure id="MacTracegif" float="1">
        <graphic fileref="MacTrace.gif" format="gif" />
      </figure>
      <formalpara>
        <title>When to trace</title>
        <para>Use this option to turn tracing off or on. For a One-time only trace, the
trace is made for the duration of the next connection. Click the Apply button
to make your selection active. This option corresponds to the Trace and
TraceAutoStop parameters in the preference files.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Custom trace library</title>
        <para>Use the Select Library button to browse the machine for a library file that
contains the code to intercept the trace output. This field should generally be left
blank. When setting this parameter, you may use the Browse button to locate
the library, or specify it manually. If specified manually, note that the location
must be specified as it would be in a Terminal session. You may use ~/ as a
shortcut to your user Home directory. This option corresponds to the TraceDLL
parameter in the preference files.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Log file path</title>
        <para>Specify the complete location of the file to which you wish to write the
trace. You may use the Browse button to locate or create the file, or specify it
manually. If specified manually, note that the location must be specified as it
would be in a Terminal session. You may use ~/ as a shortcut to your user
Home directory. This option corresponds to the TraceFile parameter in the
preference files.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <sect3 id="mactraceparams">
        <title>Trace Parameters in ODBC.INI</title>
        <para>When the ODBC tracing parameters are changed, they are saved in
the [ODBC] section of the ODBC.preference or odbc.ini file, whichever is
active on your system.
</para>
        <para>The following example is for a one time trace to sql.log file on the
active user's desktop.</para>
        <programlisting>[ODBC]
Trace         = 1
TraceAutoStop = 1
TraceDLL      =
TraceFile     = ~/Desktop/sql.log
</programlisting>
        <para>Once the tracing of a connection is complete, the Trace and TraceAutoStop
parameters will both be set to 0.</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="testmacdsn">
      <title>Testing Data Sources</title>
      <sect3 id="macodbctest">
        <title>ODBC SDK C++ Sample</title>
        <para>Use the 'ODBC SDK 2.0 C++ Sample PPC' application to test a DSN:</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass23gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass23.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>From the Environment menu, select "Open Connection...".</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass24gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass24.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Choose a User DSN, or press the File DSN tab, and select a File DSN.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass25gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass25.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>With a DSN highlighted, press OK. Input
Username and Password as appropriate, and click OK.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass15gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass15.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>From the SQL menu select Execute SQL... </para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass26gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass26.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Enter an SQL query in the dialog.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass27gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass27.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>With success, the results will be shown.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass28gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass28.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>When you QUIT the application, you will see a warning message about
your DSN connection. Please note you will continue to
consume one licensed connection until the application is
terminated.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass29gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass29.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="testmacdsniodbc">
        <title>iODBC Test PPC</title>
        <para>Use the 'iODBC Test PPC' application to test a DSN:</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass30gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass30.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Type a question mark ('?') and hit &lt;return&gt; to get a list of
available User DSNs.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass31gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass31.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Type a connect string,
using one of the listed User DSNs, following the format
DSN=&lt;DSN&gt;;UID=&lt;username&gt;;PWD=&lt;password&gt;. You may leave the
UID and/or PWD parameters out of your string; if you do, you will be
presented with the usual log-in dialog:</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass32gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass32.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>If you do not wish to type so much, need to add a DSN, or wish to
connect to a File DSN, type anything else, and hit the &lt;return&gt; key.
You will be presented with the DSN Chooser dialog, in which you may do
select an existing User or File DSN, or create a new DSN of either type.
Instructions on creation may be found earlier in this chapter.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass33gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass33.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>When the 'SQL&gt;' prompt comes up, you can enter any SQL statement,
including UPDATE, INSERT, DELETE, or SELECT, followed by &lt;return&gt;.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass34gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass34.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Results are returned in plain text, to your query window.</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass35gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass35.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>Type 'exit&lt;return&gt;' to close your DSN connection. The prompt
'Again (y/n) ?' is asking whether you wish to connect to another DSN.
Respond y(es) or n(o) and hit &lt;return&gt;. Yes brings you back
to the 'Enter ODBC string' prompt; no returns 'Have a nice day.'</para>
        <para>When you QUIT the application, you will be prompted to save the
output text. Default is "Don't save".</para>
        <figure id="MacOSClass38gif" float="1">
          <graphic fileref="MacOSClass38.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="cliinstmacosx">
    <title>Mac OS X</title>
    <sect1info>
      <keywordset>
        <keyword>Mac Client</keyword>
        <keyword>Mac OS X</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </sect1info>
    <para>OpenLink Software's components are fully supported on Mac OS X
  versions 10.1.x through 10.4.x ("Puma" to "Tiger"). In most ways, these look
  the same to users. However, there are some significant differences to be
  aware of between these Operating Systems.</para>
    <para>As shipped from Apple, Mac OS X did not include any ODBC support until
 Jaguar.  The ODBC Driver Manager, Data Source Administrator, etc. - all had
 to be delivered with the Drivers.  When Apple introduced Darwin, an Open-Source
 project meant to form the kernel of Mac OS X, OpenLink were determined to port its
 open-source iODBC Driver Manager to the new platform.  With the introduction
 of the Preview Release of Mac OS X, the traditional set of dynamic libraries
 was broadened to include a system of Frameworks to encourage the development
 of fully ODBC compliant, native Mac OS X drivers and client applications.   </para>
    <para>That set of Frameworks, along with the OpenLink ODBC Administrator
 (then known as the iODBC Administrator), has been included with all OpenLink
 installations for Mac OS X since 10.0. The OpenLink ODBC Administrator
 supports all core features of ODBC, and presents driver-specific DSN
 configuration panels, as defined by the Driver developer, through the use of
 Setup Libraries.</para>
    <para>Jaguar's release marked Apple's recognition that Data Access was an
 important part of an Enterprise Operating System.  Already part of the standard
 distribution of Darwin, the basic iODBC dynamic libraries are now a part of the
 standard installation of Mac OS X 10.2.  Apple also included their own version
 of an ODBC Administrator, as a proof-of-concept.  Apple's Administrator permits
 Driver Registration, Tracing, and all other core features of ODBC; however,
 among other hard edges, all DSN configuration must be done by manually entering
 Keyword-Value pairs. Further, the user must know what Keywords to use, along
 with their acceptable Values.</para>
    <para>The OpenLink Generic Multi-Tier Driver for ODBC for Mac OS X is
 distributed in a single disk image (.dmg) file, which contains a Macintosh Installer
 mpkg. </para>
    <para>The OpenLink ODBC Client Components for Mac OS X comprise the
 following:</para>
    <table>
      <tgroup>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Component</entry>
            <entry>Purpose</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>iODBC Driver Manager</entry>
            <entry>A shared library that links ODBC compliant applications to ODBC
  Drivers</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Generic ODBC Driver</entry>
            <entry>A shared library that provides database connectivity and data access
  services to ODBC compliant applications</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Sample ODBC Applications</entry>
            <entry>Simple programs that can be used to verify your ODBC installation
  and working environment</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <sect2 id="cliinstmacxinstall">
      <title>Installation</title>
      <para>Double-click the mpkg to start the installation process. </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX01" float="1">
        <title>OpenLinkUDA-4.5.dmg</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX01.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>You must have an Administration username and password to install the
 OpenLink Generic Multi-Tier Driver for ODBC.  The Jaguar Installer will
 immediately prompt you to enter your Mac OS X Username and Password. </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX02" float="1">
        <title>Authentication</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX02.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>The installer will display a "Welcome" message. Click "Continue". </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX03" float="1">
        <title>Welcome</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX03.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>The next screen will display the Read-Me file, including any
 last-minute updates to these documents.  Please read carefully, and click
 "Continue" when finished. </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX04" float="1">
        <title>Read Me </title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX04.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>The next screen will display the License Agreement for the OpenLink
 Single-Tier Driver for ODBC. Please read, and click "Continue". </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX05" float="1">
        <title>Software License Agreement</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX05.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
<!--
  NEED NEW GRAPHIC
-->
      <para>You will be prompted to "Agree" to continue the installation, or
 "Diagree" to abort. </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX06" float="1">
        <title>Agree or Disagree to Licensing</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX06.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
<!--
  NEED NEW GRAPHIC
-->
      <para>You will be asked to select a Destination Volume. Generally, this should
 be your Mac OS X boot volume. Click on the desired disk icon, and then
 click "Continue". </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX07" float="1">
        <title>Choose Destination</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX07.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>You may now choose the Easy Install, or if you are an experienced user,
 you may Customize which components are installed. OpenLink generally
 recommends the Easy Install.   If you have installed OpenLink or iODBC
 components in the past, click "Upgrade" to continue; otherwise, click
 "Install". </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX08" float="1">
        <title>Easy Install</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX08.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <figure id="MacOSX09" float="1">
        <title>Custom Install</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX09.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>You will be shown a graphical progress bar as Installation progresses,
 followed by System Optimization. </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX10" float="1">
        <title>Installation Progress </title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX10.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <para>When the process is complete, you will be told that the software was
 successfully installed.  Click "Close" and your new database driver for ODBC is
 ready for use! </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX11" float="1">
        <title>Installation Proceeds</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX11.png" format="png"></graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="cliinstmacxdsnconf">
      <title>Data Source Configuration</title>
      <para>The OpenLink ODBC Administrator for Mac OS X currently supports creation
 of User and System Data Source Names (DSNs). Support for File DSNs will be
 delivered in a future release. </para>
      <para>A User DSN is only available to the user who creates the data source.  Its
 parameters are stored in that user's settings file
 <computeroutput>~/Library/Preferences/ODBC.preference</computeroutput>. </para>
      <para>A System DSN is available to the whole system so that any user, including
 the system itself, will be able to use that data source.  Its parameters are stored
 in the System settings file <computeroutput>/Library/Preferences/ODBC.preference</computeroutput>.</para>
      <para>A File DSN is a special 'mobile' data source that stores the data source
 information associated with the Driver in a file, which may then be copied and
 shared among different users and ODBC application host machines. </para>
      <sect3 id="cliinstmacxusrsysdsns">
        <title>Creating User or System Data Sources</title>
        <para>The steps for creating a DSN are as follows:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Launch the OpenLink ODBC Administrator, found in the
  <computeroutput>/Applications/Utilities/</computeroutput> directory.</para>
            <figure id="MacOSX12" float="1">
              <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator icon</title>
              <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX12.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click the tab for the kind of DSN you wish to
  create - User or System.  Press the Add button to begin creating a new
  Data source. </para>
            <figure id="MacOSX13" float="1">
              <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator, User DSN tab</title>
              <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX13.png" format="png"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Select the Driver to be used to create your ODBC DSN.  In
  this example make sure "OpenLink Generic ODBC Driver" is highlighted.  Then click
  the Finish button. </para>
            <figure id="MacOSX14" float="1">
              <title>Choose an ODBC Driver</title>
              <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX14.png" format="png"></graphic>
            </figure>
            <note>
              <title>Note:</title>
              <para>The connections will not succeed until Server-side components are
  installed and properly configured.</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The ODBC Driver manager now launches the selected driver
code so that the DSN may be configured. In this example it will present the
OpenLink ODBC Data Source Configuration dialog (depicted below).</para>
            <para>Configure the fields of the ODBC "System" or "User" DSN
Configuration dialog in the manner explained below:</para>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Name</title>
              <para>(Datasource) The name of the ODBC DSN, this is how you will
interact with the OpenLink ODBC Driver from within ODBC compliant applications
once your ODBC DSN has been created.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Description</title>
              <para>Additional information that further describes the ODBC DSN that
you are creating.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Server</title>
              <para>Selected Zero Configuration service name or
<computeroutput>&lt;hostname or IP address&gt;:&lt;port&gt;</computeroutput>
of running Broker.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <para>The easiest way to complete this field is to select a machine
from the drop-down list-box. This list of servers is automatically generated
by the Zero Configuration service, so you only need to chose which machine
you wish to reach.</para>
            <para>Alternatively, enter the hostname or IP address that identifies a Server
Machine running OpenLink Server Components, that speak the OpenLink Data Access
Protocol. Follow this with a colon and the TCP/IP Port number of the Broker
to contact. This corresponds to the Listen parameter on the target Broker.</para>
            <para>This example shall now assume the selection of a server from a picklist.</para>
            <figure id="macdsn01" float="1">
              <title>OpenLink Generic ODBC Setup Dialog</title>
              <graphic fileref="mac10/macdsn01.png" format="png"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the Next button or the Connection tab.
Now select the database and configuration details:</para>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Domain</title>
              <para>This is how you pick the Database Engine Type that your ODBC DSN
is to be associated with e.g. Informix 7, Oracle 7, Progress 7 etc.</para>
              <para>The default offered from the Zero Configuration is typically accepted.
An alternative compatable Domain may be chosen for a specific customisation.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Database</title>
              <para>This is how an actual database
name within the Provider Type Domain is identified, for instance "stores7"
indicates an "Informix 7" database called "stores7".  This option corresponds to
the Database parameter in the preference files.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Connection Options</title>
              <para>This is where you place any database specific database connection
options. This field in a majority of cases should be left blank by
default.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Connect now..</title>
              <para>When this tick box is checked, a test connection
is made to verify the Data Source connection.</para>
              <para>If there is no check then the Login ID and Password fields are
ignored, and no test is performed.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Login ID</title>
              <para>The default database UserID to use when logging on to a remote
database engine (identified by the Domain above).</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Password</title>
              <para>The Password for the login of the above UserID.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <figure id="macdsn02" float="1">
              <title>OpenLink Generic ODBC Setup Dialog</title>
              <graphic fileref="mac10/macdsn02.png" format="png"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the Next button or the Options tab.</para>
            <para>Now define additonal connection parameters:</para>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Read-only connection</title>
              <para>Specify whether the connection is to be "Read-only".
Make sure the checkbox is unchecked to request a "Read/Write" connection.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Defer fetching of long data</title>
              <para>Check this box to defer the fetching of long data.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Disable interactive login</title>
              <para>Suppress the ODBC "Username" and "Password" login
dialog box when interacting with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC compliant
application.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Row Buffer Size</title>
              <para>This attribute specifies the number of records to be
transported over the network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1
to 99.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <figure id="macdsn03" float="1">
              <title>OpenLink Generic ODBC Setup Dialog</title>
              <graphic fileref="mac10/macdsn03.png" format="png"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The list of parameters for the DSN are now shown.
The Test Data Source button will trigger a test of the DSN using the
existing login parameters.</para>
            <para>Click on the Next button or the Test tab.</para>
            <figure id="macdsn04" float="1">
              <title>OpenLink Generic ODBC Setup Dialog</title>
              <graphic fileref="mac10/macdsn04.png" format="png"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
  Click Finish to save your DSN, which will then be visible in the OpenLink ODBC
  Administrator's listing. </para>
            <figure id="MacOSX17" float="1">
              <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator, User DSN tab</title>
              <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX17.png" format="png"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="cliinstmacxtsts">
      <title>Testing Data Sources</title>
      <para>Any DSN can be tested for basic connectivity, to ensure that the basic
 parameters have been set correctly, through the OpenLink ODBC Administrator.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>Click anywhere on the graphic to dismiss the About box.  Click
  OK to save your DSN, which will then be seen in the OpenLink ODBC
  Administrator's listing.
<figure id="MacOSX18" float="1">
  <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator, User DSN tab</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX18.png" format="png"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Now, to verify that your settings are correct and all is
  functional, select the new DSN, and click Test. You'll be presented with the
  following dialog:</para>
          <figure id="MacOSX19" float="1">
            <title>OpenLink Login Dialog, Identity tab</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX19.png" format="png"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Input the correct password for the username shown. You can
  connect as another user, if you wish, by simply typing a different username in the
  field. To verify that your settings have all "stuck", you can click the
  Database tab: </para>
          <figure id="MacOSX20" float="1">
            <title>OpenLink Login Dialog, Database tab</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX20.png" format="png"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The "About" tab shows you basic information about the
  Driver on which the DSN is based. </para>
          <figure id="MacOSX21" float="1">
            <title>OpenLink Login Dialog, About tab</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX21.png" format="png"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>When you click OK, your Mac will think for a moment,
  while it makes a connection to the remote Data Source.  If there is a problem
  with the connection, you will be presented with an error message, such as
  this, resulting from a bad password: </para>
          <figure id="MacOSX22" float="1">
            <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator, DSN Test, Initial Error Message</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX22.png" format="png"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If you receive two error messages, the first will usually
  provide the clues to resolution; the second is typically a generic error,
  such as this rejected connection notice: </para>
          <figure id="MacOSX23" float="1">
            <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator, DSN Test, Secondary Error Message</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX23.png" format="png"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the DSN connects as expected, you will be presented
  with this Success message: </para>
          <figure id="MacOSX24" float="1">
            <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator, DSN Test, Success Message</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX24.png" format="png"></graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <sect3 id="cliinstmacxodbctest">
        <title>iODBC Test.command (or /usr/bin/odbctest)</title>
        <para>For more thorough testing, you can use iODBC Test, a sample
  application installed along with the OpenLink Generic Driver for
  ODBC. iODBC Test is a simple command-line, ODBC compliant,
  Interactive SQL client. </para>
        <para>Either double-click the
  <computeroutput>/Applications/iODBC/iODBC Test.command</computeroutput>
  script or manually launch the Terminal application (found in
  <computeroutput>/Applications/Utilities/</computeroutput>). </para>
        <figure id="MacOSX25" float="1">
          <title></title>
          <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX25.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
        <para>If you used the script, you can skip ahead to the next paragraph;
  otherwise, ensure that the environment variables ODBCINI and ODBCINSTINI
  are set correctly and enter the command /usr/bin/odbctest. </para>
        <para>At the prompt, type a question-mark (?) followed by the ENTER key,
  to show a list of available DSNs. Enter a connect string at the next prompt,
  using the syntax:</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
DSN=<DSN Name>[;UID=<username>[;PWD=<password>]]
]]></programlisting>
        <para>Text enclosed in angle brackets &lt; &gt; should be replaced by your
  environment's specifics; text enclosed in square brackets [ ] is optional. The
  only mandatory parameter is the <computeroutput>"DSN="</computeroutput>.
  All other connect parameters may be set within the DSN itself.  User
  authentication in the connect string will override similar information stored
  in the DSN.  The following connect strings are all valid, assuming a DSN
  named test_dsn exists:</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
DSN=test_dsn
DSN=test_dsn;UID=;PWD=
DSN=test_dsn;UID=fred
DSN=test_dsn;UID=fred;PWD=
DSN=test_dsn;UID=fred;PWD=derf
]]></programlisting>
        <para>A successful connection will cause display of the Driver's full version
  string, as it reports to any client application, followed by a SQL&gt; prompt.</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
Enter ODBC connect string (? shows list, or DSN=...):
DSN=test_dsn;UID=fred;PWD=derf
Driver: 04.20.0402 OpenLink SQL Server Lite Driver
SQL>
]]></programlisting>
        <para>Once the connection is made, any valid SQL query conforming to
  ODBC syntax (where applicable) may be executed. Use the command
  &quot;quit&quot; to close the connection.</para>
        <para>If the query executes successfully you will see a table of the
  data returned by the query; if unsuccessful, you will see the entire
  error message returned from the back-end DBMS. </para>
        <para>Use the command &quot;quit&quot; to close the connection. The
  prompt Again (y/n)?  is asking whether you wish to connect to
  another DSN. Respond y(es) or n(o) and hit &lt;return&gt;. Yes
  brings you back to the Enter ODBC string prompt; no returns &quot;Have a
  nice day&quot;.</para>
        <programlisting><![CDATA[
SQL>quit
Again (y/n) ? n
Have a nice day.
]]></programlisting>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="cliinstmacxtracedsn">
      <title>Troubleshooting ODBC Connections and Sessions</title>
      <para>From the Tracing Tab of the OpenLink ODBC Administrator, the level of
 Tracing can be configured. </para>
      <figure id="MacOSX26" float="1">
        <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator, Tracing tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MacOSX26.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
      </figure>
      <formalpara>
        <title>When to trace</title>
        <para>Use this option to turn tracing off or on. For a One-time only trace, the
   trace is made for the duration of the next connection. Click the Apply button to
   make your selection active. This option corresponds to the Trace and
   TraceAutoStop parameters in the preference files.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Custom trace library</title>
        <para>Use the Select Library button to browse the machine for a library file
   that contains the code to intercept the trace output. This field should generally
   be left blank. When setting this parameter, you may use the Browse button to
   locate the library, or specify it manually. If specified manually, note that the
   location must be specified as it would be in a Terminal session. You may use
   <computeroutput>~/</computeroutput> as a shortcut to your user Home
   directory. This option corresponds to the TraceDLL parameter in the preference
   files.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Log file path</title>
        <para>Specify the complete location of the file to which you wish to write the
   trace. You may use the Browse button to locate or create the file, or specify
   it manually. If specified manually, note that the location must be specified as
   it would be in a Terminal session. You may use ~/ as a shortcut to your
   user Home directory. This option corresponds to the TraceFile
   parameter in the preference files.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Trace Parameters in Preference Files</title>
        <para>When the ODBC tracing parameters are changed, they are saved in the
   [ODBC] section of the ODBC.preference or odbc.ini file, whichever is active on
   your system.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <para>The following example shows the settings for a one-time trace to a
   sql.log on the active user's Desktop.</para>
      <programlisting><![CDATA[
[ODBC]
Trace         = 1
TraceAutoStop = 1
TraceDLL      =
TraceFile     = ~/Desktop/sql.log
]]></programlisting>
      <para>Once the tracing of a connection is complete, the Trace and
   TraceAutoStop parameters will both be set to 0.</para>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Trace</title>
        <para>This parameter corresponds to the When to trace option in the
   Tracing tab. Set to 1, tracing is on; set to 0, tracing is off.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>TraceAutoStop</title>
        <para>This parameter corresponds to the One-time only option in the
   tracing tab. Set to 1, tracing will automatically stop after the next
   connection is closed; set to 0, tracing must be manually stopped. When
   tracing is automatically stopped, the Driver Manager will set both
   Trace and TraceAutoStop parameters to 0.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>TraceDLL</title>
        <para>This parameter corresponds to the Custom trace library option in
   the tracing tab. When setting this parameter, note that the file must be fully
   specified as it would be in a Terminal session. You may use
   <computeroutput>~/</computeroutput> as a shortcut to your user
   Home directory.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
        <title>TraceFile</title>
        <para>This parameter corresponds
      to the Log file path option in the tracing tab. When setting this
      parameter, note that the file must be fully specified as it would be in
      a Terminal session. You may use <computeroutput>~/</computeroutput> as a
      shortcut to your user Home directory.</para>
        <para>As of iODBC 3.51.0, there are now more variables that may be
        included in the filename: </para>
        <formalpara>
          <title>$P</title>
          <para>This is the process-id (pid) of
        the application invoking the driver manager - allowing for per-process
        log-files</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>$U</title>
          <para>This is the user-id under which
        the process is currently running</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>$T</title>
          <para>This is the timestamp in YYYYMMDDHHmmSS format</para>
        </formalpara>
        <formalpara>
          <title>$H</title>
          <para>This is the home-directory of the
        user as whom the process is running</para>
        </formalpara>
        <para>These options are case-insensitive. Hence you can specify
        <programlisting>TraceFile=/tmp/iodbc-$U-$T-$P.log</programlisting>
        if you wish.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="occunix">
    <title>Generic Client for UNIX</title>
    <sect1info>
      <keywordset>
        <keyword>Unix Client</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </sect1info>
    <para>ODBC Driver Manager exists in various forms under UNIX, but the
definitive Driver Manager for UNIX is known as the &quot;iODBC Driver
Manager&quot;.  Additional information regarding iODBC can be obtained
from:  <ulink url="http://www.iodbc.org/">www.iodbc.org</ulink>.</para>
    <para>The OpenLink ODBC Client Components for UNIX comprise the following :</para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
      <listitem>
        <para>iODBC Driver Manager - A shared library that links ODBC
applications to ODBC Drivers</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Generic ODBC Driver - A shared library (the file "oplodbc.so"
or "oplodbc.sl") that provides database connectivity and data access services
to ODBC-based clients (these can be applications written and compiled using
the iODBC SDK)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Sample ODBC Application - A simple program that can be used to
verify your ODBC installation and working environment.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <sect2 id="uocintro">
      <title>Installation</title>
      <para>The OpenLink ODBC Client Components for UNIX are contained within a
compressed TAR archive file in the format "XXoczzzz.taz", where the "XX"
represents a two-letter platform-specific code.</para>
      <para>In addition, the optional ODBC Data Source Administrator and
JDBC Samples are contained in an archive of format "XXl5adzz.taz"
(availability varies by platform).</para>
      <para>Note: The ODBC Data Source Administrator offered for configuring the
Client Component is a stripped down version of the OpenLink Admin Assistant
used for configuring the server components.</para>
      <para>These files are automatically presented to you via the OpenLink Software
Download wizard when you enter UNIX as your client operating system.</para>
      <para>The steps that follow describe the installation process:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Move the "install.sh" and all downloaded *.taz" files to an
installation directory of your choice</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Type in one of the following commands to extract the contents
of the compressed TAR archive files:</para>
          <programlisting>
sh install.sh
</programlisting>
          <para>or</para>
          <programlisting>
install.sh
</programlisting>
          <para>or</para>
          <programlisting>
./install.sh
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Setup your operating environment by executing the command:</para>
          <programlisting>. openlink.sh</programlisting>
          <para>you can also place the following entry in your ".profile" file:</para>
          <programlisting>
. openlink.sh
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Proceed to the configuration stage of this process.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <anchor id="clientcompinstalloccunixsetodbc" /><!-- Used For Menu.Ini -->
    <anchor id="setodbc" /><!-- Used For Menu.Ini -->
    <anchor id="unixsetodbc" /><!-- Used For Menu.Ini -->
    <sect2 id="unixconfiguration">
      <title>Configuration</title>
      <para>The main configuration activity involves setting up logical references
  to the actual backend database engines that you wish to access via your UNIX
  based ODBC Driver. These local references are called Universal Data Source
  Names (UDSNs) and they are responsible for linking ODBC clients with actual
  OpenLink Data Access Drivers.</para>
      <para>The OpenLink Admin Assistant is a Server Based HTML utility that enables
  you to manage UDSNs via your Web Browser. This utility provides wizards and a
  forms based user interface for performing it's tasks.</para>
      <para>During the installation for Unix, the install.sh script will generate
  a file called bin/iodbc-admin-httpd.sh.  This is a shell script used to start
  and stop the HTTP based iODBC Administrator.  The usage is as follows:</para>
      <programlisting>
$ sh iodbc-admin-httpd.sh start  # Starts the HTTP based iODBC Administrator
$ sh iodbc-admin-httpd.sh stop   # Tries to stop the HTTP based iODBC Administrator
$ sh iodbc-admin-httpd.sh status # Shows if the program is running
</programlisting>
      <para>In the sections that follow, a step by guide and illustrative screen
  shots are used to demonstrate both approaches to setting up ODBC DSNs.</para>
      <para>In the examples below lets presume that we are trying to create a UNIX
  based ODBC DSN on our machine called "opllinux" that will connect us to a
  Microsoft SQL Database on a Windows 95/98/NT Server. The critical database
  connection and network information for this setup (aka connection attributes)
  are as follows:</para>
      <para>Network Alias of a Windows 95/98/NT/2000 Server machine (typically
  your application server) running OpenLink Server Components: "ntappserver"</para>
      <para>Network Alias of a Windows 95/98/NT/2000 Server machine running
  Microsoft SQL Server: "pluto"</para>
      <para>Microsoft SQL Server Database Name: "pubs"</para>
      <sect3 id="WizardBasedDSNs">
        <title>Wizard Based Data Source Management</title>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Start up the web-based Admin Assistant available for use,
  if not already started:</para>
            <programlisting>bash$ sh iodbc-admin-httpd.sh start </programlisting>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Open up your Internet Browser and then enter the following
  URL: http://localhost:8000/ (note the OpenLink Web Assistant listens at
  port 8000 by default, this value is set at installation time).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Expand the menu by clicking on the "Client Components
  Administration", then "Data Source Name Configuration", and "Edit Data
  Sources by Wizard".</para>
            <figure id="image16" float="1">
              <title></title>
              <graphic fileref="image16.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the "Edit ODBC Data Sources" hyperlink, this takes
  you into the actual ODBC Data Source configuration wizard.</para>
            <figure id="dsn01" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Wizard</title>
              <graphic fileref="dsn01.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click the "Add" button to commence the process of creating
  a new ODBC DSN, the wizard presents you with a list of ODBC Drivers installed
  on your system, select the driver identified as "OpenLink Generic ODBC Driver"
  and then click on the "Create DSN" button.</para>
            <figure id="image17" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Wizard</title>
              <graphic fileref="image17.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter values into the "Name", "Description" and "Server" fields as
  follows:</para>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Name</title>
              <para>Enter values that uniquely identify the DSN being created, our example
  uses the name "SQL Server on NT" to indicate that this DSN will be
  connecting you to a SQL Server database on an NT server.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Description</title>
              <para>Enter values that provide additional information that helps in
  describing the purpose of the DSN that you are creating.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Server</title>
              <para>Enter the hostname or IP address that identifies a Server
Machine running OpenLink Server Components, that speak the OpenLink Data Access
Protocol. Follow this with a semicolon and a TCPIP Port number of the Broker
to contact if the default of 5000 is not used. This field corresponds to the
Listen parameter on the target Broker.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <para>Once completed click on the "Next" button.</para>
            <figure id="image18" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Wizard</title>
              <graphic fileref="image18.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Now select the database and configuration details:</para>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Domain</title>
              <para>This is how you pick the Database Engine Type that your ODBC DSN
is to be associated with e.g. Informix 7, Oracle 7, Progress 7 etc.</para>
              <para>The default offered from the Zero Configuration is typically accepted.
An alternative compatable Domain may be chosen for a specific customisation.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Database</title>
              <para>This is how an actual database
name within the Provider Type Domain is identified, for instance "stores7"
indicates an "Informix 7" database called "stores7".  This option corresponds to
the Database parameter in the preference files.</para>
              <para>In this case our example uses the database "pubs"</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Connection Options</title>
              <para>This is where you place any database specific database connection
options. This field in a majority of cases should be left blank by
default. In this case enter valid SQL Server database server
  connection values (where "-s pluto" represent an actual SQL Server instance
  currently available on your network).</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Connect now..</title>
              <para>When this tick box is checked, a test connection
is made to verify the Data Source connection.</para>
              <para>If there is no check then the Login ID and Password fields are
ignored, and no test is performed.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Login ID</title>
              <para>The default database UserID to use when logging on to a remote
database engine (identified by the Domain above).</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Password</title>
              <para>The Password for the login of the above UserID.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <figure id="image19" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Wizard</title>
              <graphic fileref="image19.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
            <para>Click on the "Next" button.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Now define additonal connection parameters:</para>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Read-only connection</title>
              <para>Specify whether the connection is to be "Read-only".
Make sure the checkbox is unchecked to request a "Read/Write" connection.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Defer fetching of long data</title>
              <para>Check this box to defer the fetching of long data.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Disable interactive login</title>
              <para>Suppress the ODBC "Username" and "Password" login
dialog box when interacting with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC compliant
application.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Row Buffer Size</title>
              <para>This attribute specifies the number of records to be
transported over the network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1
to 99.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <figure id="image20" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Wizard</title>
              <graphic fileref="image20.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The list of parameters for the DSN are now shown.
The Test Data Source button will trigger a test of the DSN using the
existing login parameters.</para>
            <figure id="image21" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Wizard</title>
              <graphic fileref="image21.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>You have now completed entering all the values that make up
  your new ODBC DSN, these values are collectively known as your ODBC DSN
  Attributes. Click on the "Finish" button in order to store these values
  permanently on your hard disk.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the "exit" button to exit the ODBC DSN configuration wizard</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="FormBasedDSNs">
        <title>Form Based Data Source Management</title>
        <para>The OpenLink Admin assistant also allows the more experience OpenLink
ODBC user to manage ODBC DSNs via a forms based interface. Like the wizard
based approach this is done entirely from within your browser. In the sections
that follow, a step by guide and illustrative screen shots are used to
demonstrate the process of creating the same ODBC DSN created in the prior
section using the Wizard approach.</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Start up the web-based Admin Assistant available for use,
  if not already started:</para>
            <programlisting>bash$ sh iodbc-admin-httpd.sh start </programlisting>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter the following URL into your Web Browser (if the Admin
Assistant isn't already initialized): http://localhost:8000 You will be
presented with a screen similar to the one below. Notice that the "Client
Component Administration", "Data Source Names Configuration" and "Edit Data
Sources By Form" hyperlinks have been expanded.</para>
            <para>Click on the "Edit ODBC Data Sources" hyperlink to commence the process
of creating a new ODBC DSN.</para>
            <figure id="image25" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Forms</title>
              <graphic fileref="image25.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>On the right side of the Admin Assistant pane is your start
page for configuring ODBC DSNs using the Forms approach. This page presents
to you a list of currently configured ODBC DSNs on the machine. Click the
"Add" hyperlink in the Action Column</para>
            <figure id="image26" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Forms</title>
              <graphic fileref="image26.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>You are now presented with a table listing that comprises
ODBC Drivers installed on your system, move on to the row that identifies
the ODBC Driver that you will be creating your DSN for, then click on the
"New" hyperlink.</para>
            <figure id="image27" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Forms</title>
              <graphic fileref="image27.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Enter values into the fields presented on the ODBC DSN form
as follows:</para>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Name</title>
              <para>enter values that uniquely identify the DSN being created, our example
uses the name "SQL Server on NT" to indicate that this DSN will be connecting
you to a SQL Server database on an NT server.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Comment</title>
              <para>enter values that provide additional information that helps in describing
the purpose of the DSN that you are creating.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>UserName</title>
              <para>enter a valid username for the database that you are connecting to, you
can leave this blank and be prompted for values at actual database connect time.</para>
            </formalpara>
<!--
<formalpara><title>Password</title>
<para>enter a default password to use, in most cases leave this blank and be
prompted for values at actual database connect time.</para>
</formalpara>
 -->
            <formalpara>
              <title>Database Name</title>
              <para>enter the name of an actual SQL Server database, in this case our example
uses the database "pubs"</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Read-only connection</title>
              <para>check this box if you require a read only session.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>No Login Dialog Box</title>
              <para>check this box if you do not to be prompted by your ODBC Driver for
username and password dialog box at connect time.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Defer fetching of long data</title>
              <para>Check this box to defer the fetching of long data.
See the Release Notes section for more details.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Database Server</title>
              <para>enter database server connection values for the database that your are
connecting to, in this case enter valid SQL Server database server connection
values (where "-s pluto" represent an actual SQL Server instance currently
available on your network).</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Server Type</title>
              <para>enter a value that identifies the type of OpenLink Agent that will serve
your ODBC client.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Protocol</title>
              <para>Chose the type of network connection to be used from TCP/IP, SPX/IPX
and DECnet. Note some operating systems do not support all the choices.
In most cases uses TCP/IP.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Hostname</title>
              <para>enter a value that identifies the server machine running your OpenLink
Server Components.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Port</title>
              <para>Enter the TCP port number of the Broker to contact.
This corresponds to the Listen parameter on the target Broker.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Row Buffer Size</title>
              <para>enter a value that represents the number of records that you would like
your ODBC driver to retrieve during each network hop. A network hop represents
the number of times your OpenLink ODBC send a message across the network to
retrieve records from your remote database server. The feature can be used to
improve ODBC record retrieval performance.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <para>
Note: The screen shot below is a snapshot of the ODBC DSN for, click on the
right-hand scroll bar to see all the fields described above.
</para>
            <figure id="image28" float="1">
              <title>Data Source Forms</title>
              <graphic fileref="image28.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
            </figure>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Click on the "Add" button at the foot of the page to complete
the creation of your new ODBC DSN.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The DSN may then be tested, or you can return to the DSN
list.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="ODBCDriverSettings">
        <title>ODBC Driver Session Settings</title>
        <para>A number of configuration session parameters are available to
adminstrators of OpenLink ODBC Drivers, these parameters can be managed via
the Web Browser based Admin Assistant or by manually editing the file
"udbc.ini" situated in the "bin" sub-directory of your OpenLink installation
directory.  These parameter enable you tailor the behaviour of your ODBC Drivers
for UNIX in line with the requirements of your ODBC based solutions and any
general infrastructural requirements that you may have.</para>
        <para>The list of configurable session parameters and their descriptions are
as follows:</para>
        <table>
          <tgroup>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Parameter</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Default Value</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Description</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>BrokerTimeout</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>30</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The time (in secs) that the OpenLink ODBC client application will
wait for the OpenLink Request Broker to accept or reject a database
connection.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>ReceiveTimeout</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>60</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The time (in secs) that the OpenLink ODBC client will wait for
an ODBC request to be completed.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>RetryTimeout</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>5</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The amount of wait time (in secs) before the OpenLink ODBC client
attempts to re-execute a failed call. After each attempt this value is
doubled.</para>
                  <para>The life time of this value never exceeds the BrokerTimeout
during intial connection establishment, and never exceeds the ReceiveTimeout
when sessions have been established.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>SendSize</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>4096</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The size (in kilobytes) of the OpenLink ODBC client's outward bound
message packets.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>ReceiveSize</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>16000</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The size (in kilobytes) of the OpenLink ODBC client's server bound
message packets.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>DebugFile</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>empty</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>When this variable contains a valid file and path reference, all
ODBC API calls will be logged and stored in the file name referenced.
</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="Sample_App">
      <title>Sample Application</title>
      <para>OpenLink also provides a sample ODBC based dynamic SQL application that
enables you verify usability of your ODBC installation.  The sample application
is situated within the "samples" sub-directory below your OpenLink installation
directory. The ODBC sample application is called "odbctest".</para>
      <para>The following steps guide you through the process of successfully utilising
this sample application. This exercise presumes that we are connecting to a
DSN called "SQL Server on NT", which connects us to a remote SQL Server
Database hosted on a machine called "pluto" via the OpenLink Server components
on an Windows 95/98/NT/2000 application server called "ntappserver".</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Ensure that your OpenLink Request Broker is up and running on
the machine "ntappserver" (you can quickly confirm this by opening up your
browser and entering the following URL: http://ntappserver:8000 )</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>At your UNIX command prompt type in the following command:</para>
          <programlisting>
odbctest
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enter a full or partial ODBC connect string at the ODBC
applications command prompt, some examples are listed below:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>for a list of DSNs on your system enter "?"</listitem>
            <listitem>to connect to the DSN called "SQL Server on NT" type (this is
    a partial connect string): DSN=SQL Server On NT</listitem>
            <listitem>to enter a username and a blank password combination along with
    the DSN type (this is a partial connect string only because we have a seperate
    server hosting the OpenLink Server and Microsoft SQL Server components): DSN=SQL
    Server on NT;UID=sa;PWD=</listitem>
            <listitem>to enter a directive that instructs the OpenLink Server
    components to connect to the remote SQL Server hosted on the machine called
    "pluto", type the following (this is a full connect string for this
    particular scenario): DSN=SQL Server on NT;UID=sa;PWD=;OPTIONS=-s pluto</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>If the previous step is successful you are now ready to execute
SQL interactively against your remote database, to do this enter the following
SQL command:</para>
          <programlisting>
select * from authors
</programlisting>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>To quit this application type in "exit" at the SQL command
line prompt.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect2>
    <anchor id="SettingUpUDSNs" /><!-- Used For Menu.Ini -->
    <sect2 id="clientcompinstallClient_Comp_Installucconf">
      <title>UDBC Data Source Configuration</title>
      <para>UDBC shares its API with ODBC, and is provided for platforms
  that do not have a suitable ODBC driver manager - it is for legacy
  unix systems which did not support dynamic library functions. As
  such, it is deprecated, and documented here only for
  completeness.</para>
      <para>UDBC, like ODBC, is based on the notion of logical references to
  database backends through the use of Data Source Names.  Under UDBC, these
  are described as Universal Data Source Names (UDSNs) due to the cross data
  access standard nature of these Data Source Names (they are usable by
  OpenLink Drivers for ODBC and JDBC).</para>
      <para>The OpenLink Universal Data Access Driver Suite includes an HTTP
  based utility called the OpenLink Admin Assistant that enables you create,
  configure, and manage UDSNs via a Web Browser.  Since this is HTTP based, you
  can even do this remotely, security measures exist avoid unwanted
  tampering.  The Admin Assistant provides a wizards and HTML forms based
  user interfaces.</para>
      <para>You identify your UDSN file to UDBC Drivers via the Environment
  Variable "UDBCINI".  Your OpenLink UDBC SDK installation process will place
  a sample of this file in the 'doc' installation subdirectory.  The OpenLink
  shell script ("openlink.sh") will look for the runtime copy of this file in
  the 'bin' directory of your installation, and export it to the $UDBCINI
  environment variable.  Manually, the UDBCINI environment variable is set
  using the command:</para>
      <programlisting>
UDBCINI=/usr/openlink/bin/udbc.ini ; export UDBCINI
</programlisting>
      <para>The above presumes that your OpenLink installation's base directory
  is: /usr/openlink.  Use an appropriate directory in its place.</para>
      <tip>
        <title>See Also:</title>
        <para>The <link linkend="udbcsdk">UDBC Client Components SDK</link> chapter.</para>
        <para>Configuring UDBC data sources using:
  <link linkend="WizardBasedUDSNs">Wizards Based Assistant</link> or
  <link linkend="udbcformsdsnadmin">Forms Based Assistant</link>
        </para>
      </tip>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
&features_odbc;
&oraconcpoolgen;
<sect2 id="oraconpoolmtspecific">
<title>Multi-Tier-specific Connection-Pooling</title>
&oraconcpoolmt;
</sect2>
&orainstantclient;
</chapter>
