<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?>
<!-- 
  $Id: connectopts.xml,v 1.1.1.1 2004/09/09 10:45:20 cvs Exp $
  (C)Copyright 1996-2018 OpenLink Software
-->
<sect1 id="sql2kconnectopts">
<sect1info>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>ODBC Driver SQL Server</keyword>
    <keyword>Features</keyword>
    <keyword>Database support; Oracle; SQL Server; DB2; Informix; Sybase; Progress</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</sect1info>
<title>SQL Server 2000 – Connection Options</title>
<sect2 id="sql2kopts">
<title>Connection Option Parameters</title>
<para>When configuring an OpenLink SQL Server 2000 multi-tier Agent
 (sql2k_[sm]v[.exe] only and not sql_[sm]v[.exe]), the
following keywords and values may be entered in the
<emphasis>Connection Options</emphasis> section of the entry for the agent in
the Request Broker configuration file (oplrqb.ini).
All are optional.</para>
<table colsep="1" frame="all" rowsep="0" shortentry="0" tocentry="1"
	tabstyle="decimalstyle" orient="land" pgwide="0">
<tgroup align="char" charoff="50" char="." cols="4">
<colspec align="centre" colnum="1" colsep="2" colwidth="20pc"/>
<thead>
 <row>
   <entry>Key</entry><entry>Keyword</entry>
   <entry>Value(s)</entry><entry>Description</entry>
 </row>
</thead>
<tbody>
 <row>
  <entry>-A</entry><entry>ADDRESS</entry>
  <entry>Network address of the server which is running an instance of SQL Server.</entry>
  <entry>Address is usually the network name of the server, but can be other
  names such as a pipe, or a TCP/IP port and socket address.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-B</entry><entry>FALLBACK</entry>
  <entry><para>Yes (default)</para>
   <para>No</para>
   <para>Applies to SQL Server 6.5 only.</para>
  </entry>
  <entry>When yes, instructs the driver to attempt connection to a fallback
  server if connection to a primary server fails. When no, no attempt at a
  fallback connection is made. This option applies only to standby servers. It
  does not apply to a virtual server in a cluster / failover configuration.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-C</entry><entry>AUTOTRANSLATE</entry>
  <entry><para>Yes (default)</para>
   <para>No</para>
  </entry>
  <entry>When yes, ANSI character strings sent between the client and server
  are translated by converting through Unicode to minimize problems in
  matching extended characters between the code pages on the client and
  the server.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-D</entry><entry>DATABASE</entry>
  <entry>Database Name</entry>
  <entry>The name of the database which will be the default database for
  the connection. Note however, that for OpenLink Agents and Single-tier
  Drivers, this value is normally entered into a separate control on the
  Configuration module. If this control contains a name, entering this option
  as a connection option also could lead to the attempt to establish a
  connection being rejected.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-E</entry><entry>QUERYLOGFILE</entry>
  <entry>Full path, name and extension of the log file.</entry>
  <entry>This option applies only when Option –O (QUERYLOG_ON) is set to
  <emphasis>yes</emphasis>. This is the file to which data for long-running
  queries is saved.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-F</entry><entry>ATTACHDBFILENAME</entry>
  <entry>Name of the primary file of an attachable database. Include the full
  path and escape any \ characters if using a C character string variable.
  Example: c:\\MyFolder\\MyDB.mdf</entry>
  <entry><para>This database is attached and becomes the default database for
  the connection. You must also specify the database name in the parameter,
  DATABASE. However, see above for the Database option, -D.</para>
  <para>If the database was previously attached, SQL Server will not reattach
  it; it will use the attached database as the default for the connection.</para>
</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-G</entry><entry>QUERYLOGTIME</entry>
  <entry>Numeric character string</entry>
  <entry>Applies only when Option –O (QUERYLOG_ON) is set to
  <emphasis>yes</emphasis>. This specifies the threshold (in milliseconds)
  for logging long-running queries. Any query that does not get a response
  within this time is written to the long-running query log file (which is
  defined by the Option, -E, QUERYLOGFILE).</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-H</entry><entry>SERVER</entry>
  <entry>Server Name</entry>
  <entry>Name of a server which is running an instance of SQL Server on the
  network. By default, this is <emphasis>local</emphasis>.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-L</entry><entry>LANGUAGE</entry>
  <entry>SQL Server language name.</entry>
  <entry>SQL Server language name. SQL Server can store messages for multiple
  languages in sysmessages. If connecting to a SQL Server with multiple
  languages, Language specifies which set of messages are used for the
  connection.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-N</entry><entry>NETWORK</entry>
  <entry>Name of a network library dynamic-link library. E.g. dbnmpntw</entry>
  <entry>The name need not include the path and must not include the .dll
  file name extension.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-O</entry><entry>QUERYLOG_ON</entry>
  <entry><para>Yes</para>
   <para>No (default)</para>
  </entry>
  <entry>Enables or disables logging long-running query data on the
  connection.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-Q</entry><entry>QUOTEDID</entry>
  <entry><para>Yes (default)</para>
   <para>No</para>
  </entry>
  <entry>When yes, ,the SQL-92 rules regarding the use of quotation marks in
  SQL statements are applied. When no, the legacy Transact-SQL rules apply.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-R</entry><entry>REGIONAL</entry>
  <entry><para>Yes</para>
   <para>No (default)</para>
  </entry>
  <entry>When yes, client settings are used when converting currency, date,
  and time data to character data. When no, ODBC standard strings are used to
  represent currency, date, and time data that is converted to string data.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-S</entry><entry>STATSLOG_ON</entry>
  <entry><para>Yes</para>
   <para>No (default)</para>
  </entry>
  <entry>When set to <emphasis>yes</emphasis>, SQL Server ODBC driver
  performance data is captured.</entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-T</entry><entry>TRUSTEDCONNECTION</entry>
  <entry><para>Yes</para>
   <para>No (default)</para>
  </entry>
  <entry><para>When yes, Windows Authentication Mode is used for login
  validation. I.e. no User ID or Password need be supplied.</para>
  <para>When no, a User ID and password must be supplied.</para></entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-U</entry><entry>USEPROCFORPREPARE</entry>
  <entry><para>0 (default)</para>
	<para>1</para><para>2</para><para>Applies to SQL Server 6.5 only.</para>
  </entry>
  <entry>
   <para>When 0, the SQL Server ODBC driver does not create temporary stored
   procedures for SQLPrepare.
   </para>
   <para>When 1, instructs the SQL Server ODBC driver to create temporary
   stored procedures when statements are prepared with SQLPrepare. The
   temporary stored procedures are not dropped until the connection is broken. 
   </para>
   <para>When 2, the SQL Server ODBC driver creates temporary stored
   procedures for SQLPrepare, but only one procedure is created per statement
   handle and the procedure is dropped when the statement handle becomes
   invalid or a new SQL statement is prepared.
   </para>
  </entry>
 </row>
 <row>
  <entry>-W</entry><entry>ANSINPW</entry>
  <entry><para>Yes (default)</para>
   <para>No</para>
  </entry>
  <entry>When yes, the driver uses ANSI-defined behaviors for handling NULL
  comparisons, character data padding, warnings, and NULL concatenation.
  When no, ANSI defined behaviors are not exposed.</entry>
 </row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sql2kentry">
<title>Entry Format</title>
<sect3 id="sql2kodbcad">
<title>ODBC Administrator</title>
<para>Options should be entered into the ConnectOptions control in the
format:</para>
<screen>-&lt;OptionLetter1&gt; value1 -&lt;OptionLetter2&gt; value2 etc
e.g.
-C no –L English</screen>
<para>See the table above for a list of available option letters.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sql2koplrqb">
<title>Oplrqb.ini Settings</title>
<para>Connection Options are entered following the
<emphasis>ConnectOptions</emphasis> keyword. Options may be entered in
the same format as in the ODBC Configuration dialog, using key letters
as above for example:</para>
<screen>ConnectOptions = {-c no –l English}</screen>
<para>Surrounding braces (‘{‘ and ‘}’) may be used but are not necessary.</para>
<para>Alternately, the full keywords may be used. In this case, they
should be entered in the format:</para>
<screen>ConnectOptions = {Option1=value1;Option2=value2;etc}</screen>
<para>Semicolons should be used to separate items in the list. Surrounding
braces (‘{‘ and ‘}’) may be used but are not necessary. If surrounding
braces are used, any text outside the braces will be discarded. A trailing
semicolon is not necessary and ought not to be used, but should not cause
fatal errors if it is used.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id="sql2kgeneral">
<title>General</title>
<para>Items may be entered into the list in any order. They are not
case-sensitive, so upper case or lower case or a mixture of both can be used
(though this may depend on the SQL Server itself).</para>
<para>If no option key letters or keys are used, the Agent will assume that
the complete ConnectOptions entry is the name of the server running the SQL
Server database i.e. it will assume it to be a value for the keyword
<emphasis>SERVER</emphasis>. See the notes for this keyword in the table above.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="sql2kkeywords">
<title>Disallowed Keywords</title>
<para>The following Keywords should not be added to the ConnectOptions entry,
as they are set by the Agent Configuration Setup dialog, or are applied
automatically by the Request Broker:</para>
<simplelist>
 <member>APP</member>
 <member>DATABASE (see below)</member>
 <member>DRIVER</member>
 <member>DSN</member>
 <member>FILEDSN</member>
 <member>PWD</member>
 <member>UID (see below)</member>
</simplelist>
<para>If  any of the above Keywords are used, the agent will probably fail to
log on to the Database server, as duplicate Connect Options may have been
supplied.</para>
<para>Note: It is possible to add <emphasis>DATABASE=</emphasis> and
<emphasis>UID=</emphasis> entries, provided that the Database:Name and
Database:Username edit controls in the Agent Configuration dialog are left
blank. Note the comments for the keyword, <emphasis>TrustedConnection</emphasis>
above, which affects the handling of the UID keyword.</para>
<para>The OpenLink SQL2000 agent does not perform any consistency or validity
checking on the ConnectOptions entry, and passes the Connection options as
entered to the SQL Server. If invalid keywords or values, or unreadable
entries are supplied, the SQL Server may reject the login.</para>
<para>The exception is the case where the ConnectOptions entry contains no
recognizable entries, in which case it is assumed to be the value for the
keyword, <emphasis>SERVER</emphasis>. A completely corrupted ConnectOptions
entry will therefore probably try to connect to an invalid server.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
