<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="virtwhydoi">
      <title>Why Do I Need Virtuoso?</title>
      <para>You need Virtuoso because Knowledge is power or competitive advantage (depending on how
    you choose to exploit it). All Knowledge comes from Information. Information is produced
    from Data. </para>
      <para>The Internet is reducing the cost of accessing Information, thereby increasing the
    appetite and rates at which Information is produced and consumed. Unfortunately data
    required for the production of Information simply does not reside within one database
    engine within your organization. </para>
      <para>Whether you know it or not it is highly probable that the quest for critical
    information within your organization actually requires traversing several data sources
    served by numerous database engines from different database vendors.</para>
      <para>Virtuoso simply reduces the cost of bringing together data from different data sources
    with the view to accelerating the production of information by your Query Tools, Web &amp;
    Internet Application Development Environments, Traditional Application Development Tools,
    and Desktop Productivity Tools.</para>
      <para>Virtuoso enables you to compete effectively in the Information Age.</para>
      <para>One of the biggest challenges facing the uptake of XML is the
		availability of key XML Data itself. Virtuoso simplifies the process of
		creating XML data from existing HTML, syndicated XML, and SQL databases.
		Virtuoso enables real-time creation of Dynamic XML documents (DTD or
		XML Schema based) from homogeneous or heterogeneous SQL Databases "on the fly".</para>
      <para>By implementing a number of protocols in a single server solution,
		Virtuoso provides you with a unifying foundation upon which next generation
		eBusiness solutions can be developed and deployed. Virtuoso reduces the cost
		of bringing together data from different data sources and leverages this
		into increased effectiveness of your Query Tools, Web &amp; Internet Application
		Development Environments, Traditional Application Development Tools, and
		Desktop Productivity Tools. Virtuoso enables you compete effectively in the
		Information Age.</para>
      <para>OpenLink Software is an acclaimed technology innovator and leading
		vendor of High-Performance &amp; CROSS PLATFORM eBusiness solutions that
		adhere to a broad range of industry standards that include: ODBC, JDBC,
		OLE DB, SQL, WebDAV, HTTP, XML, SOAP, UDDI, WSDL, SMTP, NNTP, POP3, LDAP
		amongst others.</para>
      <para>Our product &amp; services portfolio includes a suite of
		High-Performance Universal Data Access Drivers for ODBC, OLE DB and JDBC,
		Internet Data Integration Servers, Virtual and Federated Database Engines,
		Embeddable SQL-Database Engines, Application Servers, Enterprise Portal
		Servers and professional services expertise capable of handling the most
		demanding eBusiness application development, deployment, and integration
		challenges.</para>
    </section>
