<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="vspx">
      <title>Virtuoso Server Pages for XML (VSPX)</title>
      <para>VSPX is an XML vocabulary for server generated HTML and XHTML pages
that may or may not be bound to native or third-party data sources.
VSPX is a framework for building and deploying dynamic web content atop
Virtuoso.  VSPX offers a widget set and event model which is similar to that of
GUI tool kits, providing the developer with much automation for common web
development tasks.  Many controls are tightly integrated with the Virtuoso
database, providing seamless data binding to local or remote relational and XML
data.  Server side scripting in VSPX is performed in Virtuoso/PL.  The VSPX
source code consists of HTML or XML with interspersed VSPX specific XML elements
which describe the UI control hierarchy of the page. </para>
      <para>VSPX covers the following areas:</para>
      <simplelist type="vert">
        <member>Rich set of controls, covering all basic HTML plus complex composite
  controls like data grids and tree browsers.</member>
        <member>Session management - Transparent session and session state handling
  using cookies, URL poisoning or digest authentication.</member>
        <member>Form entry validation server and client side.</member>
        <member>Single and multi-row controls for viewing and directly updating SQL
  tables, including scrolling through long result sets.</member>
        <member>Repeating and conditional instantiation of UI elements based on run
  time choices.</member>
        <member>Event model for HTTP request handling, providing distinct phases for
  creating the controls, retrieving data, processing posted data,
  preserving state and rendering for a user agent.</member>
        <member>Object oriented architecture, allowing easy definition of subclasses
  of existing controls for new functionality.  It suffices to implement a
  new SQL class with a few predefined methods and to implement an XSLT
  rule for generating the code based on the external XML syntax for the
  new control.</member>
        <member>Easy automatic generation of VSPX pages.  The pages being XML, it is
  simple to automate generating pages based on other data, such as
  automatically making table maintenance pages based on a SQL table
  definition.</member>
      </simplelist>
      <para>The VSPX development cycle consists of editing .vspx resources in the
file system or Virtuoso DAV.  The editing can take place using a
regular text editor or a supporting HTML editor.</para>
      &vspxprocmodel;
      
      &vspxobjectmodel;
      
      &vspxpageandsessionstate;
      
      &vspxappcode;
      
      &vspxexamples;
      
      &vspxeventpars;
      
      &vspxeventhandlers;
      
      <!--
 -
 -  This file is part of the OpenLink Software Virtuoso Open-Source (VOS)
 -  project.
 -
 -  Copyright (C) 1998-2020 OpenLink Software
 -
 -  This project is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
 -  under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the
 -  Free Software Foundation; only version 2 of the License, dated June 1991.
 -
 -  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
 -  WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 -  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
 -  General Public License for more details.
 -
 -  You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along
 -  with this program; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc.,
 -  51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA
 -
-->
    

      &vspx_attr_types;
      
      &vspx_controls;
      
      &vspxxforms;
      
      &vspxschema;
      
    </section>
