<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter  id="odbcintro">
<title>Overview</title>
<abstract><para>
A very brief introduction to ODBC.  A quick taster that might inspire users that may recall
previous experiences but never knew.
</para></abstract>
<chapterinfo>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>ODBC</keyword>
    <keyword>ODBC Driver</keyword>
    <keyword>ODBC Drivers</keyword>
    <keyword>Introduction</keyword>
    <keyword>Data Source</keyword>
    <keyword>About</keyword>
    <keyword>History</keyword>
    <keyword>Microsoft</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</chapterinfo>
<!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
<sect1 id="introodbc">
<title>OpenLink ODBC Driver (Single-Tier Edition) Introduction</title>
<sect2 id="aboutodbc">
<title>About ODBC</title>
<para>Open Database Connectivity (ODBC) is a Microsoft
        standard for database access. It provides a mechanism for
        desktop-based tools (word processors, spreadsheets,
        report writers, Internet/Intranet tools, for example) to
        transparently access data sources, such as databases.
        OpenLink Software provides the drivers you need to access
        your data sources from an ODBC compliant application.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="howodbcworks">
<title>How ODBC Works</title>
<para>A typical single-tier installation may consist of a
        database server, and a client that comprises the client
        networking provided by the database engine vendor and the
        OpenLink Lite ODBC driver. The client components need to
        be installed on every PC that is going to access the data.
        The ODBC driver must be accompanied by an application,
        such as Microsoft Office, which will use the driver to
        access and manipulate the data.</para>
<para>The OpenLink drivers can be used with, among others,
        the following software packages:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem><para>Microsoft Excel</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Microsoft Word</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Microsoft Access</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Crystal Report Writer</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Microsoft FrontPage98 (web page development tool)</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Visual Basic, Visual C++</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>All Visual Studio ADO components</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>All standard Microsoft Office applications use the
        Microsoft Query tool to access data.  This package must be
        installed in order for ODBC drivers to work. Microsoft
        queries can be embedded in documents and spreadsheets and
        easily reused and modified.</para>
<para>Crystal Report Writer is a stand-alone reporting tool
        that enables you to write and graph reports. It employs a
        &quot;click through&quot; user interface.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="whatcanudowodbc">
<title>What You Can Do With ODBC</title>
        <para>Everyone can do something different with ODBC. Here are just a few ideas:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem><para>Customize reports directly in Microsoft Excel </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Create (e-)mailing lists in Microsoft Word </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Write and design reports in Crystal Reports </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Create custom reporting tools or data monitoring
tools (like CorVu&apos;s Executive Alert) through applications written in Visual Basic,
C++, Java, etc. </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Render on-line information using data driven web content.   </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>And much more.....</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>
&UseODBC;
<sect1 id="furtherinfo"><title>Finding Further Information About ODBC &amp; Utilities</title>
<para>The Microsoft&reg; Data Access SDK is the primary source of
information, instruction and utilities on using data access technologies such as ODBC. Its tools,
samples, and documentation are designed to help developers create solutions for
their data access needs. For the latest news and updates about the data access
technologies, go to the Microsoft Data Access Web site
<ulink url="http://www.microsoft.com/data/" target="_blank">http://www.microsoft.com/data/</ulink></para>
<para>The MSDASDK contains a complete programmers reference
guide to ODBC as well as other data access technologies.</para>
<para>
    An online version is available at the MSDN site
<ulink url="http://msdn.microsoft.com/" target="_blank">http://msdn.microsoft.com/</ulink></para>
<para>Direct API testing applications are also available in the MSDASDK.</para>
</sect1>
</chapter>
