<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sect2 id="oraconcpoollite">
<sect3>  <title>Unix / Linux</title>
  <para>OpenLink Single-Tier (Lite) Drivers require the following environment
  variables to be set in the connecting process (shell or ODBC
  application):</para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_MIN - if not set defaults to 0</listitem>
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_INCR - if not set defaults to 1</listitem>
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_MAX - if not set defaults to OCI_CONNPOOL_MIN
    + OCI_CONNPOOL_INCR</listitem>
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_WAIT - if not set defaults to TRUE</listitem>
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_LINGER - if not set defaults to 0
      seconds</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>OCI connection pooling is disabled by setting a minimum connection
  pool size of 0.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3>  <title>Windows</title>
  <para>On Windows, when using the OpenLink Lite Driver for
  Oracle, the parameters can be configured using the Lite driver's
  setup dialog:</para>
  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_MIN - if not set defaults to 0</listitem>
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_INCR - if not set defaults to 1</listitem>
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_MAX - if not set defaults to OCI_CONNPOOL_MIN
    + OCI_CONNPOOL_INCR</listitem>
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_WAIT - if not set defaults to TRUE</listitem>
    <listitem>OCI_CONNPOOL_LINGER - if not set defaults to 0
      seconds</listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</sect3>
<sect3>
  <title>Linger Time</title>
  <para>This option is currently only available for WIN32 single-tier Oracle
  drivers</para>
  <para>Normally, when connection-pooling is enabled for an Oracle instance,
  the pool is destroyed when the last connection in use is closed. The next
  connection to the Oracle instance recreates the pool. Depending on the
  minimum size of the pool, the time taken to create it can be significant. If
  your application is designed in such a way that the connection usage count
  could regularly fall to zero (e.g. in a webserver environment), the overhead
  of the pool creation time could negate the benefits of pooling. The 'linger
  time' option can help alleviate this problem, at the cost of introducing a
  disconnection delay for the last pooled connection in use. The linger time
  should be set no longer than the pool creation time and no longer than the
  maximum disconnection time acceptable for the application.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
