<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter  id="requirements">
<title>OpenLink ODBC Driver (Single-Tier Edition) System Requirements and Basic Instructions</title>
<abstract><para>System requirements and basic installation instructions for OpenLink Single-Tier Drivers for ODBC.</para></abstract>
<chapterinfo>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>ODBC</keyword>
    <keyword>ODBC Driver</keyword>
    <keyword>ODBC Drivers</keyword>
    <keyword>Requirements</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</chapterinfo>
<!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
<sect1 id="installoverview">
<sect1info>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>Install Single-Tier ODBC</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</sect1info>
<title>Installing OpenLink Single-Tier Drivers for ODBC</title>
<para>There are five basic steps to install the product:</para>
<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Satisfy all prerequisites as listed in
    <link linkend="systemreq">System Requirements</link>
    section of this chapter.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Download the desired OpenLink Single-Tier Driver for ODBC from
    OpenLink's web site - details are in the
    <link linkend="downloading">Downloading OpenLink Lite ODBC Drivers</link>
    section of this chapter.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Save the license file that was emailed to you.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Install OpenLink Single-Tier Driver for ODBC on
    your ODBC Application Host - details are in
    <link linkend="installation">Installation Guide</link>
    chapter of this manual.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Configure the OpenLink Single-Tier Driver for ODBC - details are in
    <link linkend="datasource">Data Source Configuration Guide</link>
    chapter of this manual.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>To extend your trial, purchase a permanent license through the OpenLink Web site.
    Details are in
    <link linkend="downloading">Downloading OpenLink Lite ODBC Drivers</link>Chapter 6 of this manual.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="systemreq">
<title>System Requirements</title>
<sect2 id="softreq">
<title>Software Requirements</title>
<para>You must have the following software to use OpenLink Single-Tier Drivers for ODBC:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem><para>One or more ODBC compliant application(s).</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>A supported database server.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>The client networking software provided by the
        database vendor, installed on each client ODBC Application Host. This
        is not necessary to use the OpenLink Single-Tier Drivers for
	SQL Server, MySQL, PostgreSQL, or Virtuoso.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>The OpenLink Lite ODBC Driver corresponding to the
        database client networking version and/or database server,
        also installed on each client ODBC Application Host.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>A valid license file for each required OpenLink Driver.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="hardware">
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<para>You must have the following hardware to use OpenLink Single-Tier
Drivers for ODBC:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
  <listitem><para>A TCP/IP network connection to the database server, with a
  working connection using the client networking components, if present.
  </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>An ODBC Application Host running an operating system that is
  supported by OpenLink Lite ODBC Drivers. Currently this is Mac OS X 10.1.2
  or later, Windows 95/98/ME/NT/2000/XP, Linux &amp; Unix of the major brands.
  Check the OpenLink website &usweb; to verify availability of support for
  an operating system.
  </para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The ODBC client applications you want to use may have their own hardware or
        software requirements, which must also be satisfied. For example, Microsoft
        Office may require a minimum of 64Mb of RAM.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="downloading">
<sect1info>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>Download</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</sect1info>
<title>Downloading OpenLink Single-Tier Drivers for ODBC</title>
<para>
If you intend to use the OpenLink Lite ODBC Drivers with Microsoft Office 97,
this will require the use of an older release of the OpenLink Driver which is
compatible, but no longer available for general download. Please contact
technical support(technical.support@openlinksw.com) for details on how to
obtain these drivers.
</para>
<para>Using your Internet browser, access the OpenLink
        Software web site nearest you. The web address is: </para>
<para>North and South America: &usweb;</para>
<para>Europe, Africa: &ukweb;</para>
<para>Asia, Australia: &myweb;</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>From the OpenLink homepage, click the &quot;Software
Availability and Download&quot; link in the left-hand menu.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Click the Data Access Download button.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If this is your first download from OpenLink, or you are not
certain which product you need, please select the first button, for
Wizard-based product selection. If you are sure you know exactly what
you need, select the second button, for direct product selection.
</para>
<para>The remainder of these instructions will focus on Wizard-based
selection. Depending on your responses, you may receive fewer or more
questions in your own visit.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Answer the three initial questions:</para>
 <simplelist>
  <member>a. Indicate which type of connectivity you require, if you know.</member>
  <member>b. Select the Operating System(s) on which your ODBC and/or JDBC
  Client Application(s) will run. You may select as many as apply.</member>
  <member>c. Select the database which holds the data.</member>
 </simplelist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Indicate the data access technologies with which you have
experience or familiarity, if any.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Indicate any other data access drivers which you have
evaluated or will be evaluating for this installation.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Input your email address. If you have registered as an
OpenLink user before, input your password. If not, proceed to the
Registration Form.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Select download links from those presented. If your browser
is not set up with a default download location, you may be prompted to
choose where to save the file(s). Pay careful attention to the instructions
on this screen, as some installations may require several files, on one
or more machines.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>
Once the download is complete, you may exit your web browser.
</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Save the license file that is automatically emailed to you.
It will be needed during the install.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</sect1>
</chapter>