<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
  <sect1 id="winproductlic">
    <title>Product Licensing</title>
    <sect1info>
      <keywordset>
        <keyword>Licensing</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </sect1info>
    <sect2 id="wstartlic">
      <title>Initial License</title>
      <para>When you obtain a Data Access Driver from the OpenLink Web Site, a 
license file will automatically be emailed to you.  Please ensure the email address 
you have provided is correct.  If you obtained the Data Access Driver from a 
CD, you may need to apply for an evaluation license through our Web site, or by 
contacting one of our offices.  The standard license will provide 30 days to 
evaluate the product.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="wapplylic">
      <title>How to apply the License</title>
      <para>You will be prompted for the location of your license file during the initial 
installation.  If you have not yet received a license file, you may still install 
the product, and manually apply the license file when you do receive it.  </para>
      <para>To use the license file, simply place it in one of the following locations:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Place the license file in the default location for your Operating System. </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>For Linux and Unix -  $OPENLINK/bin. </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>For Windows -by default, C:\Program Files\OpenLink\bin. If 
   you chose a different installation target directory, the bin directory beneath 
   your choice.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>For Mac OS X - //Library/Application Support/openlink/bin.  </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>For Mac OS 9 or earlier - the Preferences folder, within the 
   System Folder.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Alternatively, you may define the environment variable 
 OPL_LICENSE_DIR to specify the directory in which all OpenLink license files 
 can be found. (Does not apply to Mac OS 9 or earlier.)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Finally, license files may reside in any directory included in 
 the PATH environment variable of the host machine. (Does not apply to 
 Mac OS 9 or earlier.) </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>License errors are generally found in the Request Broker log file, oplrqb.log.</para>
      <para>If your product fails to register properly, then your license may be 
corrupt or invalid.  Please check the license details against the name and 
version of the Driver installed, and contact OpenLink Software Technical Support 
for assistance.</para>
      <note>
        <title>Note:</title>
        <para>only the first license file found for a particular product is examined, and 
 an expired license may prevent use of an unexpired license</para>
      </note>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="getlic">
    <sect1info>
      <keywordset>
        <keyword>License Upgrading</keyword>
      </keywordset>
    </sect1info>
    <title>Upgrading the License</title>
    <para>You may purchase a permanent license key online via the Internet.  
To purchase a key follow these instructions:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Use an Internet browser to connect to one of the following
 web sites:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
          <listitem>
            <para>North and South America: &usweb;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Europe, Africa: &ukweb;</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Asia, Australia: &myweb;</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <figure id="mtlic1" float="1">
          <title>Online order</title>
          <graphic fileref="lic1.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Select the ORDER ONLINE menu link from the left side of the web page.</para>
        <para>A new web pages appears listing links to different online forms for varying products.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose the link to the correct product.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose the Client Operating System</para>
        <figure id="mtlic2" float="1">
          <title>License detail selection</title>
          <graphic fileref="lic2.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
        </figure>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose the Server Operating System</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose the Data Access Service</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose the Licensing scheme required</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Choose the Number of CPUs that are to be controlled by the license.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Add your product to the shopping cart, and follow the on
 screen instructions for completing the license purchase.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>In the event that you are unable to use the online ordering system,
then please contact sales@openlinksw.com or sales@openlinksw.co.uk to obtain
the permanent license key.</para>
  </sect1>
