<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
  $Id: UDAZeroConf.xml,v 1.1.1.1 2004/09/09 10:45:25 cvs Exp $
  (C)Copyright 1996-2018 OpenLink Software
-->
<chapter id="UDAZeroConf" >
<title>Zero Configuration Networking</title>
<abstract>
 <para>Zero Configuration Networking is a server administered service that 
 broadcasts configured available services over IP to allow clients 
 to discover and used them with no prior knowledge or client specific 
 configuration.</para>
 </abstract>
<chapterinfo>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>ODBC</keyword>
    <keyword>ODBC Driver</keyword>
    <keyword>ODBC Drivers</keyword>
    <keyword>Zero Configuration</keyword>
    <keyword>Zero Configuration Networking</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</chapterinfo>
<sect1 id="zeroconfintro"><title>Introduction</title>
<formalpara><title>What is it?</title>
 <para>Zero Configuration Networking, also known as ZeroConf, is networking that 
 needs nothing to be pre-configured and no administration to operate.  Zero 
 Configuration Networking uses industry standard IP protocols to allow devices 
 to automatically find each other without the need to enter IP addresses or 
 configure DNS servers.</para></formalpara>
 <formalpara><title>Why is it Important?</title>
 <para>ZeroConf enables services on a network built with this support to be 
 automatically discovered, thereby requiring no knowledge on the part of the 
 end user attempting to use this service about the specifics of its configuration, 
 just that it is available for use if selected.</para></formalpara>
   <para>Using ZeroConfig for installation rollouts or for site maintenance 
  can significantly reduce administration overhead.  Because the client ODBC 
  Driver is bound to a service name only, should the details of that service change 
  the client will automatically re-acquire the new details (this does not include changes 
  to the name of the service).  For example, 200 client installations configured to 
  use the service "SalesDB1",  moving the "Sales" database to another server, 
  perhaps even a different database does not required any further client 
  configuration, they will automatically connect to the new server.</para>
  <para>ZeroConf configuration on the server is kept to a minimum.  The 
  host and port number of the Request Broker are automatically supplied to the 
  ZeroConf service descriptions on the server when they are broadcast over 
  the network.  Furthermore, ZeroConf service descriptions can be based 
  directly on a Server Type that maps to a Database Agent.  
  If we consider the above example again, moving the "Sales" 
  database to another machine will not need any ZeroConf adjustment on the
  server either, the new host and port and automatically discovered and 
  broadcast with no administrator intervention other than to start the 
  new Broker and Database.</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="zerosrvconf"><title>Server Configuration</title>
<sect1info>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>Zero Configuration Server</keyword>
    <keyword>Server</keyword>
    <keyword>Zero Config</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</sect1info>
  <para>The OpenLink Multi-Tier Request Broker now has the ability to Broadcast 
  ZeroConf services of available Database agent connections on the network.  
  These can be discovered by the the OpenLink Multi-Tier ODBC client.</para>
  <sect2 id="zeroconfini"><title>Configuration by Rule Book Edit</title>
  <para>ZeroConf Support in the Request Broker is configured via the Rule Book.  
  The Rule Book now contains a new section called [Zero Config].  This section 
  contains a list of DSN="Connect String" pairs.  The DSN is the name that will 
  be presented to clients listing available ZeroConf data source, the 
  Connect String is a string of connection attributes necessary for making 
  a connection to a Database Agent as the example below shows:</para>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[
[Zero Config]
ZJDBC3= "ServerType=JDBC13;Database=virtuoso.jdbc2.Driver;UID=dba"
ZSQL2K = "ServerType=SQLServer 2000;Database=pubs;UID=sa"
SQLServer 2000="Database=pubs;UID=sa"
]]></programlisting>
  <para>The syntax is:</para>
  <programlisting>&lt;Service_name&gt;="Connect String"</programlisting>
  <para>or:</para>
  <programlisting>&lt;Server Type&gt;="Connect String"</programlisting>
  <para>In this second case, there is no Server Type defined within
  the connect string itself.</para>
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem><formalpara><title>&lt;Service_name&gt;</title>
  <para>This is the service name you want this specific ZeroConf service to be known 
  as when discovered by any Multi-Tier ZeroConf clients on the network.</para>
  </formalpara></listitem>
 <listitem><formalpara><title>Connect String</title>
 <para>A semi-colon (;) separated list of connection attributes that the Request 
 Broker will supply to clients for automatically connecting the the requested 
 DSN.  Note that these attributes can be any of those used by a normal Multi-Tier 
 client, since this is effectively making DSN-less connection string for clients 
 to use.  Host and Port cannot be specified, these are automatically supplied by 
 the broker when the service is requested.</para></formalpara>
 <note><title>Note:</title>
 <para>The Host and Port number of the Request Broker are not specifiable, 
 the Broker will supply these to the services broadcasted automatically.  This 
 brings a huge saving on administration overhead; if the circumstances of the 
 networking infrastructure change, the installation is simply moved to another 
 machine or a backup server activated, no modifications to the ZeroConf details 
 are required, and the new host:port will be automatically supplied from then on.</para></note>
 <para>The Connect String must be enclosed in double-quotes.</para>
 <para>The list of available attributes are:</para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>ServerType [SVT]</title>
   <para>Specify agent domain.  This is used by the broker to determine which 
   agent section to connect the client request to using mapping rules.</para></formalpara></listitem>
   <listitem><formalpara><title>ServerOptions</title>
   <para>Server startup options specific to agent/database.</para></formalpara></listitem>
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Database [DATABASE]</title>
   <para>Database to use. Agent/database specific.</para></formalpara></listitem> 
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Options [OPTIONS]</title>
   <para>Database connect options. Agent/database specific.</para></formalpara></listitem> 
  <listitem><formalpara><title>UserName [UID]</title>
   <para>Username to connect as.</para></formalpara></listitem> 
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Password [PWD]</title>
   <para>Password for user.</para></formalpara></listitem> 
  <listitem><formalpara><title>ReadOnly [READONLY]</title>
   <para>Specify Y(es) for read-only (ro) or N(o) for read-write (rw) 
   connections. Read only connections are sometimes faster, but can never 
   modify any database.</para></formalpara></listitem> 
  <listitem><formalpara><title>FetchBufferSize [FBS]</title>
   <para>Number of rows (records) to be fetched per call from database agent.  
   Values range from 1 to 99</para></formalpara></listitem> 
  <listitem><formalpara><title>Persist</title>
   <para>Controls whether the Zero Config DSN should be persisted on the client 
   when select. If set to Yes/Y/T then it will, and if for set to No/N/F then it will only 
   be used at connect time and not stored in the client which may be deemed a 
   securty breach.</para></formalpara></listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="zeroconfwiz"><title>Configuration by Wizard</title>
  <para>The OpenLink Universal Data Access Admin Assistant provides a 
  graphical remote access interface to the server settings such as those found 
  in the Rule Book.  This interface has been extended to support configuration of 
  the ZeroConf settings in the Server Component Administration Section, called Zero 
  Config Administration.</para>
  <para>The Zero Config Administration pages are very much like Client 
  Data Source configuration pages, they have the same layout and descriptions as 
  they are essentially data sources stored on the server.</para>
  <para>To make a new Zero Configuration entry, follow this sequence:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
  <para>From the Server Components Administration menu, chose the
  Zero Config Administration sub menu, and then Zero Config Administration by Wizard.
  A list of current confirguations is shown:</para>
<figure id="zerowiz01" float="1">
  <title>Zero Config by Wizard - Admin Assistant Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="zerowiz01.png" format="png"></graphic>
</figure>
 </listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>Press the Add button. Enter a suitable name for the configuration:</para>
<figure id="zerowiz02" float="1">
  <title>Zero Config by Wizard - Admin Assistant Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="zerowiz02.png" format="png"></graphic>
</figure>
 </listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>Enter the database details. The parameters are identical to those
  in the <link linkend="WizardBasedDSNs">ODBC DSN configuration wizard</link>.</para>
  <para>For each parameter you wish to configure, you need
  to enable it by checking the box on the left side.
  Each field is disabled until the check box is marked.</para>
<figure id="zerowiz03" float="1">
  <title>Zero Config by Wizard - Admin Assistant Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="zerowiz03.png" format="png"></graphic>
</figure>
 </listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>Enter the additional connection parameters. In same way as previous
  page, each parameter
  field needs to be enabled by the check mark on the left side.</para>
<figure id="zerowiz04" float="1">
  <title>Zero Config by Wizard - Admin Assistant Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="zerowiz04.png" format="png"></graphic>
</figure>
 </listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>The complete configuration parameters are now shown:</para>
<figure id="zerowiz05" float="1">
  <title>Zero Config by Wizard - Admin Assistant Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="zerowiz05.png" format="png"></graphic>
</figure>
 </listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>The Zero Config entry now appears in the list:</para>
<figure id="zerowiz07" float="1">
  <title>Zero Config by Wizard - Admin Assistant Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="zerowiz07.png" format="png"></graphic>
</figure>
 </listitem>
</orderedlist>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="zeroconfform"><title>Configuration by Form</title>
  <para>From the Server Components Administration menu, chose the
  Zero Config Administration sub menu, and then Zero Config Administration by Form.
The list of current configurations is shown. Chose one to edit or delete,
or select "add" to make a new configuration.</para>
<figure id="zeroform01" float="1">
  <title>Zero Config by Forms - Admin Assistant Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="zeroform01.png" format="png"></graphic>
</figure>
  <para>The parameters required in the form are the same as those detailed in the
  previous section on Rule Book Configuration.
  The Host and Port fields are not available since this information is 
  supplied by the Request Broker hosting the service.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="zeroclientconf"><title>Client Configuration</title>
<sect1info>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>Zero Configuration Client Configuration</keyword>
    <keyword>Client Configuration</keyword>
    <keyword>Zero Config</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</sect1info>
  <sect2 id="zeroclientdm"><title>Configuration by Windows ODBC Driver Manager</title>
  <para>During the configuration of a DSN in the Windows ODBC Driver Manager
  the Server field offers a drop down list of available Zero Config
  servers:</para>
<figure id="odbccl5b" float="1">
  <title>Windows ODBC Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="odbccl5.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
</figure>
</sect2>
  <sect2 id="zeroclientaa"><title>Configuration by Admin Assistant</title>
  <para>During the configuration of a DSN in the Admin Assistant
  it is currently not possible to discover the Zero Config entries.
  However on Windows it is possible to put the name of a
  Zero Config entry in the Server field.</para>
<figure id="zerowiz10" float="1">
  <title>Windows Zero Config DSN Configuration</title>
  <graphic fileref="zerowiz10.png" format="png"></graphic>
</figure>
</sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>