<chapter id="EEIntro" >
  <title>OpenLink ODBC Driver (Express Edition) Documentation</title>
  <abstract>
    <para>
      OpenLink Express Edition drivers enhance the common perception of an
      ODBC driver - a single component installed on the desktop or
      workstation machine only - by not requiring any further installation
      of database-specific networking on the client, or components on the
      database-server. Once installed, it provides seamless connectivity to
      the databases. The Express Edition drivers have been designed in
      harmony with Apple's Mac Universal Platform. Maximum capability,
      minimum effort.
    </para>
  </abstract>
  <chapterinfo>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>ODBC</keyword>
      <keyword>ODBC Driver</keyword>
      <keyword>Express Edition Drivers</keyword>
      <keyword>Mac OS X</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>
  <sect1 id="eeoverview"><title>Overview</title>
    <para>
      The OpenLink Express Edition driver is a client-only installation and
      goes some way to ensure the job for developers, administrators and
      end-users is simplified. Part of this process means installing the
      software in one location as opposed to numerous locations. By
      discarding the server-side setup, there is no server-side
      administration so the user has only a single entry-point for
      installation and administration. In the majority of cases, knowing
      the database by name is all that is required.
    </para>
    <para>
      To the developer writing an application, there is no requirement to
      know on which server it resides: you can write your application for
      any environment, regardless of where it will end. There are also
      performance benefits gained by employing this single solution, which
      in some cases exceeds that provided by the database vendor's drivers.
      Being able to integrate your solution simply into your organization
      with its plethora of internal and disparate systems means your RoI
      increases significantly.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="eearch"><title>Driver Architecture</title>
      <para>
        These drivers are built by implementing the ODBC data-access
        interface specifications directly connecting to the database. There
        are no limiting factors as with traditional Single-Tier solutions.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Express Edition drivers are Type-B- or -C-based remote
        procedure calls (RPC) interface to the wire-protocol of the
        underlying database. This is a client-only interface that
        communicates directly with the remote database server. These
        interfaces typically are unavailable to third-party developers. To
        date the Open Source projects such as FreeTDS, MySQL, PostgreSQL
        and Interbase are the only publicly accessible and freely available
        versions of such interfaces.
      </para>
      <para>
        The ODBC Express Edition drivers offer developers an opportunity to
        develop generic solutions across platforms without prior knowledge
        of the operating system hosting the Database server.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="eesysreq"><title>System Requirements</title>
      <sect3 id="eesoftreq"><title>Software Requirements</title>
        <para>You must have the following software to use OpenLink Express
        Edition ODBC Drivers:</para>
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>One or more ODBC-compliant application(s).</listitem>
          <listitem>A supported database server.</listitem>
          <listitem>The OpenLink Express Edition ODBC Driver for the target database server</listitem>
          <listitem>A valid license file for each required OpenLink Express Edition ODBC Driver.</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="eehardreq"><title>Hardware Requirements</title>
        You must have the following hardware to use OpenLink Single-Tier
        Drivers for ODBC:
        <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
          <listitem>A TCP/IP network connection to the database server from
            the client machine the Express Edition driver is installed on.
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
	    An ODBC Application Host running an operating system that is
            supported by OpenLink Express Edition ODBC Drivers. The
            currently supported operating systems are Mac OS X 10.3 (PPC),
            Mac OS X 10.4 (PPC &amp; Intel). Please check the OpenLink
            website <ulink
                       url="http://www.openlinksw.com/">http://www.openlinksw.com/</ulink>
            to verify availability of support for an operating system.
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect3>
      <para>
        The ODBC client applications you want to use may have their
        own hardware or software requirements, which must also be
        satisfied.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="eeinstallconf"><title> Installation and Configuration Guide</title>
      <para>
        This section provides a step-by-step guide for the installation and configuration of the OpenLink Express Edition drivers.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="eeinstallconfmacosx"><title>OpenLink Express Edition Drivers Installation and Configuration on Mac OS X</title>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
