<chapter id="EEMySQL" >
  <title>OpenLink ODBC Driver for MySQL (Express Edition) </title>
  <sect1 id="eemysqlmac">
    <title>OpenLink ODBC Driver for MySQL (Express Edition) for Mac OS X</title>
    <sect2 id="eemysqlmacinst">
      <title> Installation Guide</title><para>The OpenLink ODBC Driver for MySQL
        (Express Edition) is distributed as a Disk image (DMG) file. Simply
        double click on the disk image 'mul6emys.dmg' to extract the
        installer mpkg file:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-00.png"/></figure>
      <para>Double-click on the mpkg file to run the
        installer. Follow the on-screen instructions as indicated below to
        complete the installation:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-01.png"/></figure>
      <para>When prompted, permit the verification script to
        run. This simply checks to see that you are running a version of Mac
        OS X later than 10.3.0:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-02.png"/></figure>
      <para>Review the <emphasis>Welcome</emphasis> message
        to confirm you're installing the right driver:
      </para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-03.png"/></figure>
      <para>Review the <emphasis>ReadMe</emphasis> for
        installation requirements and any known issues:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-04.png"/></figure>
      <para>Please read and agree to the <emphasis>Software
          License Agreement</emphasis> before continuing your installation:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-05.png"/></figure>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-06.png"/></figure>
      <para>Select the destination volume for driver installation:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-07.png"/></figure>
      <para>Accept the default installation of the driver, or
        click <emphasis>Customize</emphasis> to select specific components for
        installation:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-08.png"/></figure>
      <para>Select the components to be installed, or
        click <emphasis>Easy Install</emphasis> to return to the default:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-09.png"/></figure>
      <para>The Software must be installed as a user with
        Administrative privileges on the machine. When prompted, provide a
        relevant username and password:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-10.png"/></figure>
      <para>Installation will proceed.</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-11.png"/></figure>
      <para>During installation, you will be prompted to select a
        license file for the driver. If such a license file already exists on
        the machine, then select the 'use existing file' option.</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-15.png"/></figure>
      <para>If you accidentally clicked this option, you can
        cancel out of the selection dialog. As the following alert will
        explain, you can manually apply the license file at any point in the
        future:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-16.png"/></figure>
      <para>A trial or permanent license may be obtained by
        selecting the <emphasis>Try and Buy</emphasis> option which loads our
        online try and buy web page:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-12.png"/></figure>
      <para>A permanent license may be obtained by clicking
        on the 'Shop' link to visit our online store, or you may obtain a
        trial license by registering with and logging in to the OpenLink Web
        site:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-13.png"/></figure>
      <para>Click on the 'Download License' button to immediately
        obtain an evaluation license file; it will be saved to your Browser's
        download folder (which typically defaults to your desktop). A message
        will also be sent to your email address with a link to your OpenLink
        Data Space (ODS) Briefcase, where all non-expired trial and full
        license files will be stored for download at your convenience.</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-14.png"/></figure>
      <para>Close the browser, and proceed as if you had
        selected the option to <emphasis>use existing file</emphasis>. Select
        the license file to be used for the installation:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-15.png"/></figure>
      <para>Installation is now complete, and you can exit the
        Installer and proceed to configure a DSN:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-17.png"/></figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="eemysqlmacconf"> <title> Configuration</title>
      <para>To configure an ODBC DSN, double-click the <emphasis>OpenLink
          ODBC Administrator.app</emphasis> located in
        /Applications/Utilities/, or the <emphasis>iODBC
          Administrator.app</emphasis> located in /Applications/iODBC/:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-18.png"/></figure>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-19.png"/></figure>
      <para>Click on the <emphasis>Add</emphasis> button, to
        create a new DSN (Data Source Name):</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-20.png"/></figure>
      <para>Choose the <emphasis>OpenLink MySQL Driver (Express
          Edition) v6.0</emphasis> from the list of available drivers. Choose
        the <emphasis>OpenLink MySQL Driver (Express Edition)(Unicode)
          v6.0</emphasis> <emphasis>if and only if</emphasis> you are working
        with multi-byte character sets, as unnecessary translations can
        significantly ODBC performance:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-21.png"/></figure>
      <para>In the <emphasis>Data Source</emphasis> tab, enter a
        suitable name and optional description for the DSN being created:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-22.png"/></figure>
      <para>The <emphasis>Connection</emphasis> tab requests the
        minimum parameters required to make a connection to the target
        database:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>Host - the name of the server on which the target
          MySQL instance is running</listitem>
        <listitem>Port - the port at which the target MySQL instance is
          listening (default 3306)</listitem>
        <listitem>Database - the name of a valid database on the target
          MySQL instance</listitem>
        <listitem>Username - a valid MySQL username</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-23.png"/></figure>
      <para>If desired, click the <emphasis>Advanced</emphasis>
        button to set additional parameters relevant to the MySQL connection.
        None of these need be changed for a basic connection:
      </para>
      <table><title></title><tgroup><thead/><tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>SocketFactoryClassName</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>The name of the class that the driver should use for
                creating socket connections to the server. This class must
                implement the interface 'com.mysql.jdbc.SocketFactory' and
                have public no-args constructor.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ConnectTimeout</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Timeout for socket connect (in milliseconds), with 0
                being no timeout.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>SocketTimeout</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Timeout on network socket operations (0, the default
                means no timeout).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>IsInteractiveClient</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Set the CLIENT_INTERACTIVE flag, which tells MySQL to
                timeout connections based on INTERACTIVE_TIMEOUT instead of
                WAIT_TIMEOUT</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>UseCompression</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Use zlib compression when communicating with the
                server (true/false)?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>AllowMultiQueries</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Allow the use of ';' to delimit multiple queries
                during one statement (true/false).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>UseSSL</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Use SSL when communicating with the server
                (true/false); defaults to 'false'.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>RequireSSL</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Require SSL connection if useSSL=true?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>AllowUrlInLocalInfile</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Should the driver allow URLs in 'LOAD DATA LOCAL
                INFILE' statements?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>Paranoid</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Take measures to prevent exposure sensitive
                information in error messages and clear data structures
                holding sensitive data when possible?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>MetadataCacheSize</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>The number of queries to cacheResultSetMetadata for if
                cacheResultSetMetaData is set to 'true'</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>BlobSendChunkSize</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Chunk to use when sending BLOB/CLOBs via
                ServerPreparedStatements</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>CacheServerConfiguration</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Should the driver cache the results of 'SHOW
                VARIABLES' and 'SHOW COLLATION' on a per-URL basis?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ElideSetAutoCommits</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>If using MySQL-4.1 or newer, should the driver only
                issue 'set autocommit=n' queries when the server's state
                doesn't match the requested state by
                Connection.setAutoCommit(boolean)?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>UseReadAheadInput</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Use newer, optimized non-blocking, buffered input
                stream when reading from the server?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>UseUnicode</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Should the driver use Unicode character encodings when
                handling strings? Should only be used when the driver can't
                determine the character set mapping, or you are trying to
                'force' the driver to use a character set that MySQL either
                doesn't natively support (such as UTF-8),
                true/false.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>CharacterEncoding</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>If 'useUnicode' is set to true, what character
                encoding should the driver use when dealing with strings?
                (defaults is to 'autodetect')</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>CharacterSetResults</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>Character set to tell the server to return results
                as.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>ConnectionCollation</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>If set, tells the server to use this collation via
                'set collation_connection'</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <emphasis>SessionVariables</emphasis></entry>
              <entry>A comma-separated list of name/value pairs to be sent
                as SET SESSION ... to the server when the driver
                connects.</entry>
            </row>
      </tbody></tgroup></table>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-24.png"/></figure>
      <para>As suggested above, the parameters of
        the <emphasis>Options</emphasis> and <emphasis>Preferences</emphasis>
        tabs need not be changed for a basic connection:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-25.png"/></figure>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Row Buffer Size</emphasis> - This attribute
          specifies the number of records to be transported over the
          network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1 to
          99.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Hide Login Dialog</emphasis> - Suppress the
          ODBC "Username" and "Password" login dialog box when interacting
          with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC compliant
          application.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Read Only connection</emphasis> - Specify
          whether the connection is to be "Read-only". Make sure the
          checkbox is unchecked to request a "Read/Write"
          connection.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Drop Catalog from Meta calls</emphasis> -
          Enable this option to have the catalog name not appear for
          tables, views and procedures when requesting database
          meta-data.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Drop Schema from Meta calls</emphasis> - Enable
          this option to have the schema-name not appear for tables, views
          and procedures when requesting database meta-data.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>SQLStatistics disabled</emphasis> - Check this
          box to have SQLStatistics() return an empty resultset. Use this
          if the underlying database does not support retrieving statistics
          about a table (e.g. what indexes there are on it).</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>No support of quoted identifier</emphasis> - If
          it is set, the call SQLGetInfo for 'SQL_IDENTIFIER_QUOTE_CHAR'
          will return the space (" "). It can be used if DBMS doesn't
          support quoted SQL such as select * from "account"</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>No support of search string escape</emphasis> -
          If it is set, the call SQLGetInfo for 'SQL_LIKE_ESCAPE_CLAUSE'
          will return the space (" "). It can be used if DBMS doesn't
          support SQL escape patterns</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Patch of NULL size of SQL_CHAR</emphasis> - If
          set this option overrides the size of SQL_CHAR column type
          returned by the database with the value set in the text box (in
          bytes). With the default value of 0 the driver uses the size
          returned by the database.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>SQL_DBMS Name</emphasis> - Manually override
          the SQLGetInfo(SQL_DBMS_NAME) response returned by the driver.
          This is know to be required for products like Microsoft InfoPath
          for which the return the value should be "SQL Server".</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-26.png"/></figure>
      <listitem><emphasis>Initialization SQL</emphasis> - Lets you
        specify a file containing SQL statements that will be run against the
        database upon connection, automatically.</listitem>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Cursor Sensitivity</emphasis> - Enables or
          disables the row version cache used with dynamic cursors. When
          dynamic cursor sensitivity is set high, the Cursor Library
          calculates checksums for each row in the current rowset and
          compares these with the checksums (if any) already stored in the
          row version cache for the same rows when fetched previously. If
          the checksums differ for a row, the row has been updated since it
          was last fetched and the row status flag is set to
          SQL_ROW_UPDATED. The row version cache is then updated with the
          latest checksums for the rowset. From the user's point of view,
          the only visible difference between the two sensitivity settings
          is that a row status flag can never be set to SQL_ROW_UPDATED
          when the cursor sensitivity is low. (The row status is instead
          displayed as SQL_ROW_SUCCESS.) In all other respects, performance
          aside, the two settings are the same - deleted rows don't appear
          in the rowset, updates to the row since the row was last fetched
          are reflected in the row data, and inserted rows appear in the
          rowset if their keys fall within the span of the rowset. If your
          application does not need to detect the row status
          SQL_ROW_UPDATED, you should leave the 'High Cursor Sensitivity'
          checkbox unchecked, as performance is improved. The calculation
          and comparison of checksums for each row fetched carries an
          overhead. If this option is enabled, the table oplrvc must have
          been created beforehand using the appropriate script for the
          target database.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>MaxRows Override</emphasis> - Allows you to
          define a limit on the maximum number of rows to returned from a
          query. The default value of 0 means no limit.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable AutoCommit</emphasis> - Change the
          default commit behaviour of the OpenLink Express Edition Driver.
          The default mode is AutoCommit mode (box unchecked).</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable Rowset Size Limit</emphasis> - Disable
          the limitation enforced by the cursor library. The limitation is
          enforced by default to prevent the Driver claiming all available
          memory in the event that a resultset is generated from an
          erroneous query is very large. The limit is normally never
          reached.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Defer fetching of long data</emphasis> - Defer
          fetching of LONG (BINARY, BLOB etc.) data unless explicitly
          requested in query. This provides significant performance
          increase when fields in query does not include LONG data
          fields.</listitem>
        <listitem><emphasis>Multiple Active Statements Emulation</emphasis>
          - Enables use of Multiple Active statements in an ODBC
          application even if the underlying database does not allow this,
          as it is emulated in the driver.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click on the <emphasis>Test Data Source</emphasis>
        button to make a connection to the database to verify connectivity:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-27.png"/></figure>
      <para>Enter a valid username and password for the target
        database:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-28.png"/></figure>
      <para>A successful connection to the database has been made:</para>
      <figure><graphic
                 fileref="ee-mys-29.png"/></figure>   
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="eemysqlwin">
    <title>OpenLink ODBC Driver for MySQL (Express Edition) for
      Windows</title>
    <sect2 id="eemysqlwininst"> <title>Installation</title>
      <para>The OpenLink ODBCDriver for MySQL(Express Edition) is distributed as a Windows MSI installer. Simply double click on the installer 'ntl6emys.msi' to commence the installation: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst01.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Installer Welcome Dialog for the OpenLink ODBCDriver for MySQL(Express Edition): </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst02.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Please read the software license agreement and accept before continuing your installation: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst03.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Before installation you will be prompted for a license file. If a license file already exists on the machine, then select the 'use exisiting file' option. A trial (try) or full (buy) license can be obtained by selecting the 'try and buy' option, which loads OpenLink's online try and buy web page: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst04.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>To obtain the trial license, you must be a registered user on the OpenLinkWeb site and login with your username (e-mail address) and password. Click on the 'Shop' link to visit OpenLink's online shop cart to purchase a full license, if required: </para>
      <para>Click on the 'download license' button to immediately obtain the license file and save it to your desktop. Alternatively, an auto-generated e-mail will be sent to your registered e-mail address. This email will contain a link to your OpenLinkData Space ( ODS). The OpenLinkData Space ( ODS) contains copies of all trial and full license files in a Briefcase for download at a later date. </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst05.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Select the license file to be used for the installation: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst06.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Choose to perform a custom, typical or complete installation of the driver: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst07.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Select the features to be installed: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst08.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Click the install button to begin the installation of components: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst09.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Installation in progress: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst10.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>The Software installation is complete and ready for use: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysinst11.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="eemysqlwinconf"> <title>Configuration</title>
      <para>To configure an ODBCDSN, run the ODBCAdministrator located in the Administrative Tools section of the Control Panel: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf01.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Click on the Drivers tab to confirm the OpenLink MySQL ODBCDriver [Express Edition][6.0] has been successfully installed: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf02.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>From either the User or System DSN tabs, click on the Add button and select the OpenLink MySQL ODBCDriver [Express Edition][6.0] from the list : </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf03.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>In the Data Source tab, select a suitable DSN name and optional description for the Data Source to be created: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf04.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>The Connection tab requests the minimum parameters required to make a connection to the target database: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf05.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Host</emphasis>: This is the fully qualified
          hostname or IP address of the machine hosting the DBMS you
          wish to access, e.g., dbms-server.example.com, or
          192.168.155.123. Any hostname which will be resolved by your
          local DNS
          is acceptable.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Port</emphasis>: This is the port on which MySQL is
          listening</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Database</emphasis>: This is the name of the
          MySQL
          database to which you want to connect</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Login ID</emphasis>: This is a valid user name for
          the MySQL database</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Password</emphasis>: This is a valid password for
          the MySQL database</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click next to verify that all settings are correct or uncheck the check box to delay testing to a later stage. </para>
      <para>The advanced button displays additional, optional parameters that can be configured: </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf06.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <table>
        <title/>
        <tgroup>
          <thead/>
          <tbody>
            <row>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                SocketFactoryClassName</entry>
              <entry>The name of the class that the driver
                should use for creating socket connections to the server.
                This class must implement the interface
                'com.mysl.jdbc.SocketFactory' and have no-args
                constructor.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                ConnectTimeout</entry>
              <entry>Timeout for socket connect (in
                milliseconds), with 0 being no timeout.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                SocketTimeout</entry>
              <entry>Timeout on network socket operations
                (0, the default means no timeout).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                IsInteractiveClient</entry>
              <entry>Set the CLIENT_INTERACTIVE flag,
                which tells MySQL to timeout connections based on
                INTERACTIVE_TIMEOUT instead of WAIT_TIMEOUT.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                UseCompression</entry>
              <entry>Use zlib compression when
                communicating with the server (true/false).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                AllowMultiQueries</entry>
              <entry>Allow the use of ';' to delimit
                multiple queries during one statement (true/false).</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>UseSSL</entry>
              <entry>Use SSL when communicating with the
                server (true/false), defaults to 'false.'</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>RequireSSL</entry>
              <entry>Require SSL connection if
                useSSL=true.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                AllowURLInLocalInfile</entry>
              <entry>Should the driver allow URLs in 'LOAD
                DATA LOCAL INFILE' statements?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Paranoid</entry>
              <entry>Take measures to prevent exposure
                sensitive information in error messages and clear data
                structures holding sensitive data when possible?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                MetadataCacheSize</entry>
              <entry>The number of queries to
                cacheResultSetMetadata for if cacheResultSetMetaData is set
                to 'true.'</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                BlobSendChunkSize</entry>
              <entry>Chunk to use when sending BLOB/CLOBs
                via ServerPreparedStatements.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                CacheServerConfiguration</entry>
              <entry>Should the driver cache the results
                of 'SHOW VARIABLES' and 'SHOW COLLATION' on a pre-URL
                basis?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                ElideSetAutoCommits</entry>
              <entry>If using MySQL 4.1 or
                newer, should the driver only issue 'set autocommit=n'
                queries when the server's state doesn't match the requested
                state by Connection.setAutoCommit (boolean)?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                UseReadAheadInput</entry>
              <entry>Use newer, optimized non-blocking,
                buffered input stream when reading from the server?</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>UseUnicode</entry>
              <entry>Should the driver use Unicode
                character encodings when handling strings? Should only be
                used when the driver can't determine the character set
                mapping or you are trying to 'force' the driver to use a
                character set that MySQL either doesn't natively support (such
                as UTF-8), true/false.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                CharacterEncoding</entry>
              <entry>If 'useUnicode' is set to true, what
                character encoding should the driver use when dealing with
                strings? (defaults to 'autodetect')</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                CharacterSetResults</entry>
              <entry>Character set to tell the server to
                return result as.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                ConnectionCollation</entry>
              <entry>If set, tells the server to use this
                collation via 'set collation_connection.'</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                SessionVariables</entry>
              <entry>A comma-separated list of name/value
                pairs to be sent as SET SESSION to the server when the
                driver connects.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>As indicated above, the parameters on the options and preferences tabs are not required for a basic connection. </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf17.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Drop Catalog name from DatabaseMetaData
            calls</emphasis> - Enable this option to have the catalog name
          not appear for tables, views, and procedures when requesting
          database meta-data.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Drop Schema name from DatabaseMetaData
            calls</emphasis> - Enable this option to have the schema-name
          not appear for tables, views, and procedures when requesting
          database meta-data.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Return an empty ResultSet for
            SQLStatistics</emphasis> - Check this box to have
          SQLStatistics() return an empty resultset. Use this if the
          underlying database does not support retrieving statistics
          about a table, e.g., what indexes there are on it.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable support of quoted identifier</emphasis> -
          If it is set, the call SQLGetInfo for
          'SQL_IDENTIFIER_QUOTE_CHAR' will return the space (" "). It
          can be used if the DBMS does not support quoted SQL, e.g., select
          * from "account."</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable support of search pattern escape</emphasis>
          - If it is set, the call SQLGetInfo for
          'SQL_LIKE_ESCAPE_CLAUSE' will return the space (" "). It can
          be used if the DBMS does not support SQL escape
          patterns.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Patch of NULL size of SQL_CHAR</emphasis> - If set,
          this option overrides the size of SQL_CHAR column type
          returned by the database with the value set in the text box
          (in bytes). With the default value of 0, the driver uses the
          size returned by the database.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf08.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable Interactive Login</emphasis> - Suppress the
          ODBC
          "Username" and "Password" login dialog box when interacting
          with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC compliant
          application.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Row Buffer Size</emphasis> - This attribute
          specifies the number of records to be transported over the
          network in a single network hop. Values can range from 1 to
          99.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Max rows override</emphasis> - Allows you to define
          a limit on the maximum number of rows to be returned from a
          query. The default value of 0 means no limit.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Initial SQL</emphasis> - Lets you specify a file
          containing SQL statements that will be automatically run
          against the database upon connection.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Dynamic Cursor Sensitivity</emphasis> - Enables or
          disables the row version cache used with dynamic cursors.
          When dynamic cursor sensitivity is set high, the Cursor
          Library calculates checksums for each row in the current
          rowset and compares these with the checksums (if any) already
          stored in the row version cache for the same rows when
          fetched previously. If the checksums differ for a row, the
          row has been updated since it was last fetched, and the row
          status flag is set to SQL_ROW_UPDATED. The row version cache
          is then updated with the latest checksums for the rowset.
          From the user's point of view, the only visible difference
          between the two sensitivity settings is that a row status
          flag can never be set to SQL_ROW_UPDATED, when the cursor
          sensitivity is low. (The row status is instead displayed as
          SQL_ROW_SUCCESS.) In all other respects, performance aside,
          the two settings are the same - deleted rows do not appear in
          the rowset, updates to the row since the row was last fetched
          are reflected in the row data, and inserted rows appear in
          the rowset if their keys fall within the span of the rowset.
          If your application does not need to detect the row status
          SQL_ROW_UPDATED, you should leave the 'High Cursor
          Sensitivity' checkbox unchecked, as performance is improved.
          The calculation and comparison of checksums for each row
          fetched carries an overhead. If this option is enabled, the
          table oplrvc must have been created beforehand using the
          appropriate OpenLink script for the target database.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Enable logging to the log file:</emphasis> -
          Specifies the full path to a text file. If the associated
          checkbox is checked, and a file is passed, the driver will
          log auto-generate a clientside ODBC trace.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf09.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable AutoCommit</emphasis> -
          Change the default commit behaviour of the OpenLink
          Driver. The default mode is AutoCommit (box
          unchecked).</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Disable Rowset Size Limit</emphasis> - Disable the
          limitation enforced by the cursor library. The limitation is
          enforced by default to prevent the Driver claiming all
          available memory in the event that a resultset generated from
          an erroneous query is very large. The limit is normally never
          reached.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>Multiple Active Statements Emulation</emphasis> -
          Enables use of Multiple Active statements in an ODBC application
          even if the underlying database does not allow this, as it is
          emulated in the driver.</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem><emphasis>SQL_DBMS Name</emphasis> - Manually override the
          SQLGetInfo(SQL_DBMS_NAME)
          response returned by the driver. This is required for
          products like Microsoft InfoPath for which
          the return value must be "SQL Server".</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click on the <emphasis>Test Data Source</emphasis>button to verify that a successful connection can be made to the database. </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="EEWinmysconf10.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
