<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<refentry xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xml:id="fn_identity_value">
      <refmeta>
        <refentrytitle>identity_value
</refentrytitle>
        <refmiscinfo>sql
</refmiscinfo>
      </refmeta>
      <refnamediv>
        <refname>identity_value
</refname>
        <refpurpose>returns the last assigned identity column value
</refpurpose>
      </refnamediv>
      <refsynopsisdiv>
        <funcsynopsis xml:id="fsyn_identity_value">
          <funcprototype xml:id="fproto_identity_value">
            <funcdef>integer 
<function>identity_value
</function>

</funcdef>
            <paramdef choice="opt"/>
          </funcprototype>
        </funcsynopsis>
      </refsynopsisdiv>
      <refsect1 xml:id="desc_identity_value">
        <title>Description
</title>
        <para>This function returns the value assigned to an identity column
  by the previous insert statement.  Insert statements that do not
  assign identity columns do not affect this.  Note that tables that
  have no primary key have n invisible identity column called _IDN.
  The scope is the connection.  This function may be called from a
  client or from a stored procedure and will return the last given
  identity column value wherever it was given.
  The value  stays set until overwritten by the next insert  operation.  This value is not
  set by rexecute or inserts to remote tables with autoincrement columns declared on the remote database since there is no standard way of getting this information from  remote data sources.</para>
        <para>
  The same value can be more efficiently  accessed from clients using the SQLGetStmtOption ODBC call with the option SQL_GETLASTSERIAL.  In this case the value is of type SQLINTEGER.

</para>
      </refsect1>
      <refsect1 xml:id="ret_identity_value">
        <title>Return Types
</title>
        <para>The value assigned to an identity column by the previous insert or 0 if no identity column was assigned.
</para>
      </refsect1>
      <!--
  <refsect1
xml:id="errors_identity_value">
    <title>Errors</title>
    <para>This function can generate the following errors:</para>
    <errorcode></errorcode>
  </refsect1>
  <refsect1
xml:id="examples_identity_value">
    <title>Examples</title>
    <example
xml:id="ex__19"><title></title>
      <para></para>
      <screen><![CDATA[
]]>
</screen>
    </example>
  </refsect1>
  -->

      <!--
  <refsect1
xml:id="seealso_identity_value">
    <title>See Also</title>
    <para><link linkend="fn"><function></function></link></para>
  </refsect1>
  -->

    </refentry>
