<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sect1 id="lt64bitinst">
<title>Windows (64-bit)</title>
<para>The OpenLink Single-Tier Driver for ODBC is distributed in a single
    windows msi file. Simply run the required installer wal5xxxx.msi or
    wil5xxxx.msi for Opteron (AMD64) and Itanium (IA64) respectively, which
    will display the following Welcome message:
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst1">
<graphic fileref="win64inst1.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
<para>The next screen will display the License Agreement for use with the
    OpenLink Lite Driver product. Please read this. If you agree, then
    select the accept checkbox and continue:
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst2">
<graphic fileref="win64inst2.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
<para> The next screen will prompt you the location of the folder containing a
valid license file for the required driver. Should the license file not be
available at the time of installation then select the check box provided to by
pass this stage and continue the installation: 
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst2a">
<graphic fileref="win64inst2a.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
<para>Chooses the type of installation to perform, noting that typical and
complete will immediately install the default or complete components
respectively, otherwise select the custom option which also the compenents to
be installed to be chosen: 
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst3">
<graphic fileref="win64inst3.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
<para>Assuming you chosen the custom installation option you will then be
    promptied with the option to change the installation directory if
    required:
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst4">
<graphic fileref="win64inst4.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
<para>Next you have presented with the option to choose which components
    are to be installed:
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst5">
<graphic fileref="win64inst5.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
<para>A final confirmation screen is displayed for review prior to
    performing the installation:
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst6">
<graphic fileref="win64inst6.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
<para>The installer status bar is then displayed indicating the progress
    and status of the the installation:
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst7">
<graphic fileref="win64inst7.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
<para>If the installation is successful a final dialog with be displayed
    indicating this:
</para>
<figure float="1" id="win64inst8">
<graphic fileref="win64inst8.gif"></graphic>
</figure>
</sect1>
