<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sect1 id="osxliteconf">
  <sect1info>
    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Mac OS X Data Source</keyword>
      <keyword>Features</keyword>
      <keyword>Database support; Oracle; SQL Server; DB2; Informix; Sybase; Progress</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </sect1info>
  <title>Mac OS X Data Source Configuration</title>
  <sect2 id="osxodbcsetup">
    <title>Creating ODBC Data Sources</title>
    <para>OpenLink Software's components are fully supported on Mac OS X
      version 10.1.x ("Puma") and 10.2.x ("Jaguar"). In most ways, this looks
      the same to users. However, there are some significant differences to be
      aware of between these Operating Systems.</para>
    <para>As shipped from Apple, Mac OS X did not include any ODBC support
      until Jaguar. The ODBC Driver Manager, Data Source Administrator, etc.
      - all had to be delivered with the Drivers.</para>
    <para>When Apple introduced Darwin, an Open-Source project meant to form
      the kernel of Mac OS X, OpenLink determined to port its open-source iODBC
      Driver Manager  to the new platform. With the introduction of the Preview
      Release of Mac OS X, the traditional set of dynamic libraries was
      broadened to include a system of Frameworks to encourage the development
      of fully ODBC compliant, native Mac OS X drivers and client applications.
    </para>
    <para>That set of Frameworks, along with the OpenLink ODBC Administrator
      (then known as the iODBC Administrator), has been included with all
      OpenLink installations for Mac OS X since 10.0. The OpenLink ODBC
      Administrator supports all core features of ODBC, and presents
      driver-specific DSN configuration panels, as defined by the Driver
      developer, through the use of Setup Libraries.</para>
    <para>Jaguar's release marked Apple's recognition that Data Access was
      an important part of an Enterprise Operating System. Already part of the
      standard distribution of Darwin, the basic iODBC dynamic libraries are now
      a part of the standard installation of Mac OS X 10.2. Apple also included
      their own version of an ODBC Administrator, as a proof-of-concept. Apple's
      Administrator permits Driver Registration, Tracing, and all other core
      features of ODBC; however, among other hard edges, all DSN configuration
      must be done by manually entering Keyword-Value pairs. Further, the user
      must know what Keywords to use, along with their acceptable Values.</para>
    <sect3 id="osxconfigdsn">
      <title>Mac OS X ODBC Data Sources</title>
      <para>
        The OpenLink ODBC Administrator for Mac OS X currently supports
	creation of User and System Data Source Names (DSNs). Support for File
	DSNs will be delivered in a future release.
      </para>
      <para>
        A User DSN is only available to the user who creates the data source.
	Its parameters are stored in that user's settings file
	~/Library/Preferences/ODBC.preference .
      </para>
      <para>
        A System DSN is available to the whole system so that any user,
	including the system itself, will be able to use that data source.
	Its parameters are stored in the System settings file
	/Library/Preferences/ODBC.preference.
      </para>
      <para>
	A File DSN is a special 'mobile' data source that stores the data
	source information associated with the Driver in a file, which may
	then be copied and shared among different users and ODBC
	application host machines.
      </para>
      <para>
        The steps for creating a DSN are as follows:-
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Launch the OpenLink ODBC Administrator, found in the
	    /Applications/Utilities/ directory.
          </para>
          <figure id="osxlitedmicon" float="1">
            <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator icon</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/OpenLink Admin/OpenLink ODBC Admin icon.gif" format="gif">
            </graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Click the tab for the kind of DSN you wish to create -- User or
	    System. Press the Add button to begin creating a new Data source.
          </para>
          <figure id="osxlite-502" float="1">
            <title>iODBC Data Source Administrator</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/OpenLink Admin/User DSN tab.gif" format="gif">
            </graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Select the Driver to be used to create your ODBC DSN. In this example
	    the "OpenLink SQL Server Lite Driver" is highlighted. Then click the
	    Finish button.
          </para>
          <figure id="osxlite-503" float="1">
            <title>Choose an ODBC Driver</title>
            <graphic fileref="mac10/OpenLink Admin/Choose a Driver.gif" format="gif">
            </graphic>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You will now be presented with the ODBC Data Source Configuration
	    dialog for the driver selected. Generally, there will be several tabs,
	    most of which will need some information.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxtabdatasource">
      <title>Common Data Source Tab</title>
      <para>
        First is the Data Source Tab. The parameters on this tab are similar
	(not identical) for all OpenLink Single-Tier drivers. This tab always
	holds the Name and Description parameters. Generally, it will also
	include parameters describing the target database host - Hostname,
	Port, and, if the Driver handles more than one DBMS, Server Type.
	Specific information will be presented for each Driver, below.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>DSN</title>
            <para>
              The name of the ODBC DSN. This is how you will generally refer
	      to this data source, from within ODBC client applications.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Description</title>
            <para>
              Any extra information you wish to note about the DSN you are
	      creating. This is generally not displayed by ODBC client
	      applications, though it is available to them.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Hostname</title>
            <para>
              This is the fully qualified hostname, or IP address, of the
	      machine hosting the DBMS you wish to access, e.g.,
	      dbms-server.example.com, or 192.168.155.123. Any hostname
	      which will be resolved by your local DNS is acceptable.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Server Type</title>
            <para>
              Select the version and/or vendor of the DBMS engine you will be
	      accessing, from the list presented. If your exact version is
	      not listed, try the closest version available. If that fails,
	      please contact OpenLink Technical Support.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxtabconn">
      <title>Common Connection Tab</title>
      <para>
        The second and possibly third tab hold fields specific to the database
	communications layer. The name(s) of the tab(s), the fields, and their
	data, are specific to each database. The database specific settings
	are detailed further in the text. The following list will allow you
	to quick jump to the relevent section (if reading on-line):
      </para>
      <simplelist>
        <member><link linkend="osxliteusemysql">MySQL</link>
        </member>
        <member><link linkend="osxliteuseora">Oracle 8 (or 9)</link>
        </member>
        <member><link linkend="osxliteusepost">PostgreSQL</link>
        </member>
        <member><link linkend="osxliteusesql">SQL Server</link>
        </member>
        <member><link linkend="osxliteusevirt">Virtuoso</link>
        </member>
      </simplelist>
      <para>Common fields are:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>User name</title>
            <para>
              This specifies the default username to be used when attempting
	      to make a connection. You may override this at run time.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Row Buffer Size</title>
            <para>
              This attribute specifies the number of records to be returned
	      in a chunk. Values may range from 1 to 999. Setting this value
	      too high or too low can significantly impact performance.
	      Generally, best results are achieved with values between 50
	      and 150.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Hide Login Dialog</title>
            <para>
              Suppress the ODBC "Username" and "Password" login dialog box
	      when interacting with your ODBC DSN from within an ODBC
	      compliant application. Please note &mdash; this requires that
	      these values be correctly specified within the DSN, which can
	      open a security hole.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Read Only connection</title>
            <para>
              Specify whether the connection is to be "Read-only". Make sure
	      the checkbox is unchecked to request a "Read/Write" connection.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxtabpref">
      <title>Common Preferences Tab</title>
      <para>
        The Preferences tab parameters are also generally common across all
	OpenLink Single-Tier Drivers for ODBC. All Preferences parameters
	are defined here, though they may not all appear on your Driver.
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Initialization SQL</title>
            <para>
              Lets you specify a file containing SQL statements that will be
	      run against the database upon connection, automatically.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>MaxRows Override</title>
            <para>
              Allows you to limit the maximum number of rows to return from a
	      query. The default value of 0 means no limit.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Enable Microsoft Jet Engine Options</title>
            <para>
              Extra support or altered functionality for better compatibility
	      with Microsoft Jet using applications such as Microsoft Access.
	      This generally doesn't apply to Macintosh applications; however,
	      we retain the option.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Disable AutoCommit</title>
            <para>
              Change the default commit behaviour of the OpenLink Lite Driver.
	      The default mode is AutoCommit mode (box unchecked).
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Disable Rowset Size Limit</title>
            <para>
              Disable any limitation enforced by the cursor library. The
	      limitation is enforced by default, to prevent the Driver
	      claiming all available memory when a result set is very large.
	      The limit is normally never reached.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>High Cursor Sensitivity</title>
            <para>
              Enables or disables the row version cache used with dynamic
	      cursors.
            </para>
            <para>
              When dynamic cursor sensitivity is set high, the Cursor Library
	      calculates checksums for each row in the current rowset and
	      compares these with the checksums (if any) already stored in the
	      row version cache for the same rows when fetched previously. If
	      the checksums differ for a row, the row has been updated since
	      it was last fetched and the row status flag is set to
	      SQL_ROW_UPDATED. The row version cache is then updated with the
	      latest checksums for the rowset.
            </para>
            <para>
              From the user's point of view, the only visible difference
	      between the two sensitivity settings is that a row status flag
	      can never be set to SQL_ROW_UPDATED when the cursor sensitivity
	      is low. (The row status is instead displayed as
	      SQL_ROW_SUCCESS.) In all other respects, performance aside,
	      the two settings are the same - deleted rows don't appear in
	      the rowset, updates to the row since the row was last fetched
	      are reflected in the row data, and inserted rows appear in the
	      rowset if their keys fall within the span of the rowset.
            </para>
            <para>
              If your application does not need to detect the row status
	      SQL_ROW_UPDATED, you should leave the 'High Cursor Sensitivity'
	      checkbox unchecked, as performance is improved. The calculation
	      and comparison of checksums for each row fetched carries an
	      overhead.
            </para>
            <para>
              For this option to take effect, the table 'oplrvc' must already
	      have been created, using the appropriate script for the target
	      database.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Defer fetching of long data</title>
            <para>
              Checked by default, this parameter determines whether long-data
	      fields are retrieved after all other fields in a query, or in
	      whatever order they appear in the query. Performance is
	      generally best with this enabled; hence the default setting.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
  <sect2 id="osxliteusemysql">
    <title>MySQL</title>
    <sect3 id="osxmysqlliteds">
      <title>Data Source tab</title>
      <figure id="osxmysqlds" float="1">
        <title>MySQL Data Source tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MySQL/Data Source tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxmysqlliteconn">
      <title>Connection tab</title>
      <figure id="osxmysqlconn" float="1">
        <title>MySQL Connection tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MySQL/Connection tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxmysqllitepref">
      <title>Preferences tab</title>
      <figure id="osxmysqlpref" float="1">
        <title>MySQL Preferences tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/MySQL/Preferences tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
  <sect2 id="osxliteuseora">
    <title>Oracle 8 (or 9)</title>
    <sect3 id="osxoraliteds">
      <title>Data Source tab</title>
      <figure id="osxorads" float="1">
        <title>Oracle Data Source tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/Oracle 8 and 9/Data Source tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
      <figure id="osxoradir" float="1">
        <title>Choose Oracle Directory dialog</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/Oracle 8 and 9/Choose Oracle Directory.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
      <figure id="osxoranet" float="1">
        <title>Net Service Name Editor tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/Oracle 8 and 9/Net Service Advanced.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxoraconn">
      <title>Connection tab</title>
      <figure id="osxoraconnf" float="1">
        <title>Oracle Connection tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/Oracle 8 and 9/Connection tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxoralitepref">
      <title>Preferences tab</title>
      <figure id="osxorapref" float="1">
        <title>Oracle Preferences tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/Oracle 8 and 9/Preferences tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
  <sect2 id="osxliteusepost">
    <title>PostgreSQL</title>
    <sect3 id="osxpostds">
      <title>Data Source tab</title>
      <figure id="osxpostdsf" float="1">
        <title>PostgreSQL Data Source tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/PostgreSQL/Data Source tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxpostliteconn">
      <title>Connection tab</title>
      <figure id="osxlitepost" float="1">
        <title>PostgreSQL Connection tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/PostgreSQL/Connection tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxpostlitepref">
      <title>Preferences tab</title>
      <figure id="osxpostpref" float="1">
        <title>PostgreSQL Preferences tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/PostgreSQL/Preferences tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
  <sect2 id="osxliteuseoj">
    <title>ODBC-JDBC Lite Bridges for Java</title>
    <sect3 id="osxojds">
      <title>Data Source tab</title>
      <figure id="osxojdsf" float="1">
        <title>ODBC-JDBC Lite Bridge Data Source tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/ojosxset1.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxojliteconn">
      <title>Connection tab</title>
      <figure id="osxojpost" float="1">
        <title>ODBC-JDBC Lite Bridge Connection tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/ojosxset2.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxojliteopt">
      <title>Options tab</title>
      <figure id="osxojopt" float="1">
        <title>ODBC-JDBC Lite Bridge Options tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/ojosxset3.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxojlitepref">
      <title>Preferences tab</title>
      <figure id="osxojpref" float="1">
        <title>ODBC-JDBC Lite Bridge Preferences tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/ojosxset4.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
  <sect2 id="osxliteusesql">
    <title>Microsoft or Sybase SQL Server (TDS)</title>
    <sect3 id="osxsqlin">
      <title>Installation</title>
      <para>The OpenLink ODBC Driver for Microsoft SQL Server for Mac OS X is
        distributed in a single disk image (.dmg) file, which contains a
        Macintosh Installer mpkg.
      </para>
      <para>Double-click the mpkg to start the installation process.
      </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Dmgfile.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>You will encounter a warning message that will ask you if you are
        sure that you want to install the software click to continue.
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Warning.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>The installer will display a "Welcome" message. Click "Continue."
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Welcome.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>The next screen will display the Read-Me file, including any
        last-minute updates to these documents. Please read carefully and
        click "Continue" when finished.
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Readme.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>The next screen will display the License Agreement for the
        OpenLink Single-Tier Driver for ODBC. Please read and click
        "Continue".
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_License.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>You will be prompted to "Agree" to continue the installation or
        "Disagree" to abort.
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Agree.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>You will be asked to select a Destination Volume. Generally, this
        should be your Mac OS X boot volume. Click on the desired disk icon
        and then click "Continue".
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Destination.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>You may now choose the Easy Install, or if you are an experienced
        user, you may Customize which components are installed. OpenLink
        generally recommends the Easy Install.
      </para>
      <para>If you have installed OpenLink or iODBC components in the past,
        click "Upgrade" to continue; otherwise, click "Install".
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Easyinstall.png"/>
        </figure>  
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Custominstall.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>You must have an Administration username and password to install
        the OpenLink driver. Enter your Mac OS X Username and Password.
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Authenticate.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>You will be shown a graphical progress bar as the Installation
        progresses, followed by System Optimization.
      </para>
      <para>You will need to locate the license file.
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_Selectlicense.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_Browselicense.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>When the process is complete, you will be told that the software
        was successfully installed. Click "Close" and your new database
        driver for ODBC is ready for use.
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Success.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxsqlconf">
      <title>Configuration</title> 
      <para>To configure an ODBC DSN, run theOpenLink iODBC Administrator
        located in the /Applications/iODBC folder:
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_iODBC.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Click the System DSN tab: 
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_System.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Click the Add button. Then, select theOpenLink SQL Server Lite
        Driver from the list of available drivers:
      </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Available.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <para>Click Finish. </para>
      <para>The Data Source tab prompts for a DSN name, description, and
        information that identifies the target SQL Server DBMS.
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_DSNName.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <emphasis> DSN
          </emphasis> - A brief and meaningful title for your Data Source Name
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis> Description
          </emphasis> - An optional description for your Data Source Name
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Server Name
          </emphasis> - Select the drop down list box to invoke the
          driver's Dynamic discovery of SQL Server instances on the
          network and choose the desired instance.
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Use the "Advanced" button to manually configure a connection
        if the SQL Server instance could not be dynamically located, as
        detailed below.
      </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Advanced.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Server Type </emphasis> - An OpenLink proprietary
          parameter that associates the connection with a particular TDS
          version
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Hostname
          </emphasis> - The hostname or IP address on which SQL Server
          listens
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Port  number
          </emphasis> - The TCP port on which SQL Server lists
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Server Name
          </emphasis> - SQL Server instance name on the specified host. A
          SQL Server instance can also be specified by appending
          "\InstanceName" to the ServerName, ie
          "ServerName\InstanceName".
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Mirror Host
          </emphasis> - The name of the Failover Server hosting the mirrored
          database if configured
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Use strong encryption of data
          </emphasis> - Enable SSL encryption of data between driver and
          database
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Use Mars
          </emphasis> -  
          <emphasis>M
          </emphasis>ultiple 
          <emphasis>A
          </emphasis>ctive 
          <emphasis>R
          </emphasis>esult 
          <emphasis>S
          </emphasis>ets enables the concurrent processing of multiple statements/queries and/or result sets on a single connection
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Verify Server Certificate
          </emphasis> - Verify the Database Server SSL certificate against the one specified in the "CA file" field
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>CA file
          </emphasis> - Specify the location of a Valid SSL Certificate for use during the connection
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click OK to continue. </para>
      <para>The Connection Tab takes a combination of required and
        optional parameters required to make a connection to the target
        database:
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_ConnTab.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>User name
          </emphasis> - A valid SQL Server user name
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Choose a database, charset, language to use with the
            data source
          </emphasis> -
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Password
          </emphasis> - A valid SQL Server password
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Database
          </emphasis> - The SQL Server database
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Language
          </emphasis> -
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Character set
          </emphasis> -
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Disable character set translation
          </emphasis> -
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click Continue. </para>
      <para>The Options tab enables you to set some standard and SQL
        Server-specific parameters.
      </para>
      <para>
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Options.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Row Buffer Size
          </emphasis> - This attribute specifies the number of records to be
          transported over the network in a single network hop. Values can
          range from 1 to 99.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Hide Login Dialog
          </emphasis> - Suppresses the ODBC "Username" and "Password"
          login dialog boxes when interacting with your ODBC DSN from
          within an ODBC compliant application.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Read Only connection
          </emphasis> - Specifies whether the connection is "Read-only."
          Make sure the checkbox is unchecked to request a "Read/Write"
          connection.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>TDS packet size
          </emphasis> - A value that determines the number of bytes per
          network packet transferred from the database server to the client.
          The correct setting of this attribute can improve performance. When
          set to 0, the initial default, the driver uses the default packet
          size as specified in the Sybase server configuration. When set to
          -1, the driver computes the maximum allowable packet size on the
          first connect to the data source and saves the value in the system
          information. When set to x, an integer from 1 to 10, which
          indicates a multiple of 512 bytes (for example, Packet Size of 6
          means to set the packet size to 6 * 512 equal 3072 bytes). For you
          to take advantage of this connection attribute, you must configure
          the System 10 server for a maximum network packet size greater than
          or equal to the value you specified for Packet Size.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Prepare Method
          </emphasis>- This option is specific to the TDS Driver for MS &amp;
          SQL Server SQLServers. It can take the values None, Partial Full
          (connectoptions -O [0, 1, 2] respectively). It is used to determine
          whether stored procedures are created on the server for calls to
          SQLPrepare.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>No Quoted Identifiers</emphasis>- This option indicates
          that the underlying driver does not support quoted identifiers,
          which is required for Jet engine based products like MS Access.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Use ANSI nulls, padding and warnings
          </emphasis>- This option affects TDS agent &amp; Lite Driver
          connections to MS SQLServer databases. SQL Server connectivity is
          not affected.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Map Serializable to Snapshot isolation level
          </emphasis> - Enable Snapshot transaction isolation level in
          the driver. Snapshot Isolation is a new transaction isolation
          level available in SQL Server 2005
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>SQL_DBMS Name
          </emphasis> - Manually overrides theSQLGetInfo(SQL_DBMS_NAME)
          response returned by the driver. This is required for products
          like MicrosoftInfoPath for which the return the value should be
          "SQL Server".
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click Continue to view additional preferences that can be set for
        the connection.
        <figure>
          <graphic fileref="lite_osx_sql_SQL_Preferences.png"/>
        </figure>
      </para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Initialization SQL
          </emphasis> - Lets you specify a file containing SQL statements
          that will be run automatically against the database upon
          connection.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Cursor Sensitivity
          </emphasis> - Enables or disables the row version cache used with
          dynamic cursors. When dynamic cursor sensitivity is set high, the
          Cursor Library calculates checksums for each row in the current
          rowset and compares these with the checksums (if any) already
          stored in the row version cache for the same rows when fetched
          previously. If the checksums differ for a row, the row has been
          updated since it was last fetched and the row status flag is set to
          SQL_ROW_UPDATED. The row version cache is then updated with the
          latest checksums for the rowset. From the user's point of view, the
          only visible difference between the two sensitivity settings is
          that a row status flag can never be set to SQL_ROW_UPDATED when the
          cursor sensitivity is low. (The row status is instead displayed as
          SQL_ROW_SUCCESS.) In all other respects, performance aside, the two
          settings are the same. Deleted rows don't appear in the rowset.
          Updates to the row since the row was last fetched are reflected in
          the row data, and inserted rows appear in the rowset, if their keys
          fall within the span of the rowset. If your application does not
          need to detect the row status SQL_ROW_UPDATED, you should leave the
          'High Cursor Sensitivity' checkbox unchecked, as performance is
          improved. The calculation and comparison of checksums for each row
          fetched carries an overhead. If this option is enabled, the table
          oplrvc must have been created beforehand using the appropriate
          script for the target database.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>MaxRows Override
          </emphasis> - Allows you to define a limit on the maximum
          number of rows to be returned from a query. The default value
          of 0 means no limit
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Enable Microsoft Jet Engine options
          </emphasis> -
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Disable rowset size limit
          </emphasis> - Removes OpenLink's default 100-row rowset restriction
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Defer fetching of long data
          </emphasis> - Defers fetching of LONG (BINARY, BLOB etc.) data
          unless explicitly requested in a query. This provides significant
          performance increases when fields in query do not include LONG data
          fields.
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <emphasis>Multiple Active Statements Emulation
          </emphasis> -
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Click the Finish button to save your new Data Source
        Name. </para>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
  <sect2 id="osxliteusevirt">
    <title>Virtuoso</title>
    <sect3 id="osxvirtliteds">
      <title>DSN tab</title>
      <figure id="osxvirtds" float="1">
        <title>Virtuoso DSN tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/Virtuoso/DSN tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxvirtliteident">
      <title>Identity tab</title>
      <figure id="osxlitevirtid" float="1">
        <title>Virtuoso Identity tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/Virtuoso/Identity tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Adjust Clock</title>
            <para>
              When selected the ???? will ??? for daylight saving changes.
	      This is so that ???.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Choose a Database</title>
            <para>
              If selected the pick options for the Database name and Character
	      set are accessed from the datasource.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Password</title>
            <para>
              This field is enabled if the above field is checked. Password
	      is used to make a connection to the datasource to obtain the
	      choices for subsequent fields.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Database</title>
            <para>
              The name of the Virtuoso database that is to be
	      accessed by the data source. This is a dynamically generated
	      menu, showing only those databases actually available on the
	      data source when the DSN is configured. If you need to manually
	      specify this information, you may edit the appropriate
	      ODBC.preference text file. Please contact OpenLink Technical
	      Support, for assistance.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Character Set</title>
            <para>
              The name of an installed character set on the Virtuoso server.
	      The default is the setting active on the Virtuoso Server.
	      This is a dynamically generated menu, showing only those
	      databases actually available on the data source when the DSN is
	      configured. If you need to manually specify this information,
	      you may edit the appropriate ODBC.preference text file.
	      Please contact OpenLink Technical Support, for assistance.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
    <sect3 id="osxvirtlitepref">
      <title>Security tab</title>
      <figure id="osxvirtpref" float="1">
        <title>Virtuoso Security tab</title>
        <graphic fileref="mac10/Virtuoso/Security tab.gif" format="gif">
        </graphic>
      </figure>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>Encrypted</title>
            <para>
              Enable encryption.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <formalpara>
            <title>PKCS#12 file</title>
            <para>
              Name of certificate file to be used.
            </para>
          </formalpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect3>
  </sect2>
  <!-- ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== ~~~~~ ===== -->
  <sect2 id="osxodbctesting">
    <title>Testing the ODBC Data Source</title>
    <para>
      Once an ODBC Data Source has been configured, you can test it by
      highlighting the desired DSN and clicking the Test button, on the User
      DSN or System DSN tabs of the OpenLink ODBC Administrator. This will present
      you with the following multi-tab dialog box, with the opportunity to
      override any of the DSN parameters on the fly.
    </para>
    <figure id="osxlite-507" float="1">
      <title>OpenLink ODBC Administrator</title>
      <graphic fileref="mac10/Testing/osxlite17.gif" format="gif">
      </graphic>
    </figure>
    <figure id="osxlite-508" float="1">
      <title>SQL Server Single-Tier DSN Connection Test, Identity tab</title>
      <graphic fileref="mac10/Testing/osxlite18.gif" format="gif">
      </graphic>
    </figure>
    <figure id="osxlite-509" float="1">
      <title>SQL Server Single-Tier DSN Connection Test, Connection tab</title>
      <graphic fileref="mac10/Testing/osxlite19.gif" format="gif">
      </graphic>
    </figure>
    <figure id="osxlite-510" float="1">
      <title>SQL Server Single-Tier DSN Connection Test, Preferences tab</title>
      <graphic fileref="mac10/Testing/osxlite20.gif" format="gif">
      </graphic>
    </figure>
    <figure id="osxlite-511" float="1">
      <title>SQL Server Single-Tier DSN Connection Test, About tab</title>
      <graphic fileref="mac10/Testing/osxlite21.gif" format="gif">
      </graphic>
    </figure>
    <para>
      When all parameters are as desired, click Connect, and a successful test
      will bring the following message:
    </para>
    <figure id="osxlite-512" float="1">
      <title>DSN Connection Test Results</title>
      <graphic fileref="mac10/Testing/osxlite22.gif" format="gif">
      </graphic>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Unsuccessful test connections may present any of a number of error
      messages. To resolve those errors, please refer to the troubleshooting
      section of this manual.
    </para>
    <para>
      For more thorough testing, you can use odbctest, a sample application
      installed along with the OpenLink Lite Driver. odbctest is a simple
      command-line, ODBC compliant, Interactive SQL client.
    </para>
    <para>
      It may be accessed through the Terminal application, by issuing the
      command <programlisting>/Library/iodbc/bin/odbctest</programlisting>
    </para>
    <para>
      At the SQL command prompt enter "?" for a list of ODBC DSNs on your
      machine, or enter a valid ODBC Connect String (e.g., with the DSN
      created above, named "DEMO", you would enter:
      <programlisting>DSN=DEMO;UID=&lt;Username&gt;;PWD=&lt;Password&gt;</programlisting>).
    </para>
    <para>
      From here, any valid SQL Statement may be executed. Generally, you will
      need to know a valid table name within the database to be able to
      retrieve information from it. Within odbctest, the command 'tables' will
      return a list of all tables accessible through your active connection.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the query executes successfully you will see a table of the data
      returned by the query; if unsuccessful, you will see the entire error
      message returned from the backend DBMS.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>
