<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<sect1 id="productlic"><title>Product Licensing</title>
<sect1info>
  <keywordset>
    <keyword>Product Licensing</keyword>
    <keyword>Licensing</keyword>
  </keywordset>
</sect1info>
<sect2 id="startlic">
<title>Initial License</title>
<para>When you obtain a Data Access Driver from the OpenLink Web Site,
a license file will automatically be emailed to you. Please ensure the email
address you have provided is correct. If you obtained the Data Access Driver
from a CD, you need to apply for an evaluation license through our WEB site,
or by contacting one of our offices. The standard license will provide 30days to
evaluate the product.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="applylic">
<title>How to apply the License</title>
<para>The easiest way is to let the installer place the file in the correct
location. However if the license file is not present during the install,
then you will need to apply it manually. In this case, to use the license
file, simply place it in one of the following locations:</para>
<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
<listitem><para>Place the license file in the default location for
your Operating System.</para>
<simplelist>
<member>For Linux and Unix - $OPENLINK/bin.</member>
<member>For Windows - The lite32 directory beneath the target directory of
your choice. By default this will be C:\Program Files\OpenLink\lite32.</member>
<member>For Mac OS X - /Library/Application Support/openlink/bin</member>
<member>For Mac OS 9 or earlier - the Preferences folder, within the System Folder.</member>
</simplelist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Alternatively, you may define the environment variable OPL_LICENSE_DIR to
specify the directory in which all OpenLink license files can be found.
(Does not apply to Mac OS 9 or earlier.)</para></listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Finally, license files may reside in any directory included in the
PATH environment variable of the host machine.
(Does not apply to Mac OS 9 or earlier.)</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
License errors are returned through the normal SQLError API call.</para>
<para>If your Lite Driver fails to register properly, then your license
may be corrupt or invalid. Please check the name and version of the Driver
from the About Tab, and contact OpenLink Software for assistance.</para>
<para>Note that only the first license file found for a particular
product is examined.</para>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="getlic">
<title>Upgrading the License</title>
<para>You may purchase a permanent license key online via the Internet.  
To purchase a key follow these instructions:</para>
<orderedlist>
 <listitem><para>Use an Internet browser to connect to one of the following web sites:</para>
   <itemizedlist mark="bullet">
     <listitem><para>North and South America: &usweb;</para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>Europe, Africa: &ukweb;</para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>Asia, Australia: &myweb;</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
    <figure id="fg-605" float="1">
    <title>Online order</title>
    <graphic fileref="lic1.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
    </figure>
 </listitem>
 <listitem><para>Select the ORDER ONLINE menu link from the left side of the web page.</para>
 <para>A new web pages appears listing links to different online forms for varying products.</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Choose the link to the correct product.</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Choose the database type you require for your license</para>
    <figure id="lic2" float="1">
    <title>License database selection</title>
    <graphic fileref="lic2.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
    </figure>
 </listitem>
 <listitem><para>Choose the type of license required to meet your needs.</para>
     <figure id="lic3" float="1">
    <title>License type selection</title>
    <graphic fileref="lic3.gif" format="gif"></graphic>
    </figure>
 </listitem>
 <listitem><para>Follow the on screen instructions for completing the license purchase.</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>In the event that you are unable to use the online ordering system,
then please contact sales@openlinksw.com to obtain a
permanent license key.</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>
